<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dvp_082">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with George Cooke</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
        <idno type="DDHI">dvp_082</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="9">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="COOKE"/>
        <person xml:id="MANNES"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2016-05-07"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="MANNES">This is <persName>David [J.] Mannes</persName>, and today is
        <date when="2016-05-07">May 7th, 2016</date>, and I am here with <persName>George [A.] Cooke</persName>
        [Jr.] on a phone interview. And how are you today?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I’m very well, thank you. And yourself?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">I’m doing fabulous. So I want to start this interview off way back in the
        beginning and possibly, actually, a little bit before the beginning. So could we start with
        just talking a little bit about your parents: where they’re from, their backgrounds?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I’d be happy to do that. My father is of Russian background. His family came to
          <placeName>the United States</placeName> around the turn of the last century.
        My grandfather and his family were clerics. My grandfather came to <placeName>the United
          States</placeName> as a representative of the Russian Orthodox Church.
        He was indeed a civil servant. The Russian Orthodox Church at that point
        was actually a branch of the tsarist government. At the end of the First World
          War [<name type="event">World War I</name>], as you’re probably aware, <name
          type="event">the Russian Revolution</name> radically changed the political situation in
          <placeName>Russia</placeName>, with the result that my paternal grandparents’ expectations
        of at some point returning to <placeName>Russia</placeName> ended. My father’s family was
        liquidated by the <orgName>Bolsheviks</orgName> during <name type="event">the Russian Civil
          War</name> in the early 1920s, and as a result had a very strong feeling of
        anti-communism in their—in their background.My mother was born in
          <placeName>Bremen</placeName>, <placeName>Germany</placeName>, in the 1920s.
        My maternal grandparents came to <placeName>the United States</placeName> in
          <date when="1926">1926</date> as a result of the disarray in the German economy, the hyperinflation
        and the collapse of the currency. My grandfather, my maternal grandfather was a German
        officer in the <name type="event">First World War</name>, spent three years in the trenches, was wounded
        several times and highly decorated, so it was a martial history on my mother’s side of the
        family.My father, who was a painter and a commercial artist, served in <orgName>the United
          States Army</orgName> from <date when="1940">1940</date> to <date when="1945">1945</date>, so also experience in the <orgName>military</orgName>
        on that side of my family.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I can go into more detail, or other aspects that are—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">No, that’s—that’s—that’s perfect. And what kind of work did they both do?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">My—my—my father was trained as a commercial artist at <orgName>Pratt
          Institute</orgName> in <placeName>New York</placeName>, but graduated in
        <date when="1929">1929</date>, just in time for <name type="event">the crash</name>[the Great
        Depression], so in the end became an art teacher for many years in the
          <placeName>New York City</placeName> school system while still practicing various aspects
        of his artistic calling.My mother graduated from high school at the age of 14
        in <date when="1940">1940</date> and immediately began working as a model, both an artist’s model and a
        runway model in <placeName>New York City</placeName>. Subsequently, she worked in a number
        of different capacities, primarily in the fashion industry. She ran the showroom for
          many years for one of the leading fur industry manufacturers in
          <placeName>the Garment District</placeName> in <placeName>New York</placeName>.Her real
        love in life, however, was archaeology. As an adult, she went back to school and obtained
        her bachelor’s degree, you know, in her 50s with a major in archaeology and ancient
        history.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay, wonderful.So I have this—I might be jumping a little bit forward here,
        but I have this background in your family now, of your—your father—your father’s side comes
        from <placeName>Russia</placeName>, cleric background and so strongly anti-communism because
        of what happened there. And your mother came from <placeName>Germany</placeName>. As well,
          <placeName>Germany</placeName> also had very strong anti-communist feelings at the time as
        well. So this kind of builds up to what’s coming up, I guess.But right from there, we’ll
        segue into your childhood, so can you tell me when and where you were born?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I was born on <date when="1947-10-23">October 23rd, 1947</date>, in
          <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>. We raised in and around
          <placeName>New York City</placeName>, initially in <placeName>Queens</placeName>, in
          <placeName>Middle Village</placeName>, until I was seven years old. When I
        was seven years old, along with many of their contemporaries, my parents moved
        from <placeName>New York City</placeName> out to <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, where I
        grew up. Effectively was educated in a working-class neighborhood on the south shore of
          <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, called <placeName>Uniondale</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Uniondale. Okay.So can you tell me a little bit about what the neighborhoods
        were like, first growing up till you were seven in <placeName>Queens</placeName> and then a
        little bit about <placeName>Long Island</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Sure. Obviously, the more recent memories are clearer, but—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Of course, yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—in terms of—yeah, in terms of <placeName>Middle Village</placeName>, which is
        located in <placeName>Queens</placeName>, it’s a somewhat insular community that at that
        time still had some rural aspects to it. We lived in a house with my grandparents, where,
        you know, there was a raspberry—raspberries growing. There were still some farms in
          <placeName>Queens</placeName> at that point. It was before it was greatly developed. It
        was primarily a working-class neighborhood, once again. Most of my friends’ parents at that
        point had not been to college., They typical family in the area, you know, would have been a
        policeman, a fireman, you know, a union worker.I was, you know,—my education began in the
          <placeName>New York City</placeName> school system, at <placeName>P.S. 128 [The Lorraine Tuzzo,
          Juniper Valley Elementary School]</placeName>, which at that point—you know, a
        working-class community, an integrated community, although mostly of, I would say, middle
        European ethnic background.When I—when my parents moved out to <placeName>Long
          Island</placeName>, we were, you know, a part of a huge wave of migration of working-class
        families from the city out to <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, the sort of post-war baby
        boom generation. We lived in a small tract house in a community that was, again, primarily
        working-class, very heavily ethnic in its—in its origins.Very strong presence of
          the Catholic Church. We lived on a street that was down the road from
          the Catholic Church, and Masses went from six in
        the morning until four in the afternoon. The ethnic composition of the neighborhood was
        primarily Irish, Italian and Polish. There was a small, you know, group of, you know,
        original settlers who went back to the Dutch that had colonized <placeName>Long
          Island</placeName> in the 17th century.There was also a—a black community
        that was part of <placeName>Uniondale</placeName> that had been in that area since [American] <name type="event"
          >Civil War</name> era, so it was a very well-established, working-class black community,
        and a very small, you know, presence of, you know, Jewish families, mostly, you know, from
          Central Europe, a lot of Russian and Polish folks of Jewish
        religion.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Okay.And so growing up, which schools did you attend? You mentioned
        one—I can’t remember the name—T.S. [sic] 28, you said?</u>
      <u who="COOKE"><placeName>Public School 128</placeName> in <placeName>Queens</placeName>, <placeName>New
          York</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES"><placeName>Public School 128</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Then I attended a local elementary school for second and third grade,
          <placeName>Cedar Street School</placeName>. After third grade, I moved to a—what would also be
        a grammar school. In those days, they ran from—run up to sixth grade, so from
        the fourth to sixth grade I was at <placeName>California Avenue School</placeName>. Then I went
        to what was then called the junior high school, the equivalent of what today
        would be a middle school, called <placeName>Lawrence Road Junior High School [now
        Lawrence Road Middle School]</placeName>. And then my ninth—actually, my 10th, 11th and 12th
          years were spent at <placeName>Uniondale High School</placeName>, which at that point
        was a thoroughly new organization. It had been founded in <date when="1955">1955</date>. I graduated in
          the tenth year class, in <date when="1965">1965</date>. Previously, our community was
        part of the larger town to our west, which was called <placeName>Hempstead</placeName>, and
        still is, <placeName>Hempstead</placeName>, <placeName>Long Island</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Gotcha.And so these are the schools you attended, and we
        spoke a bit about your neighborhood. So what—what events shaped your childhood, growing up?
        Whether it was from the neighborhood, how that kind of impacted you, your family
        backgrounds, the schools, themselves—what would you say kind of you grew up doing?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, it’s a broad question, but I’ll try to take a cut at it. You know, I
        guess, a view to the particular piece of history that you’re interested in. I think along
        with many of my contemporaries, I—I grew up in—in a context of the—of <name type="event">the
          Cold War</name>. One of my earliest memories is of seeing troops returning from <name
          type="event">the Korean War</name>. This would have been <date when="1953">1953</date>. And I grew up
        in a—in a community and in an age cohort in which the vast majority of our parents had, in
        one way or another, been directly affected by <name type="event">the Second World War</name>
          [<name type="event">World War II</name>]. And there was, you know, a sense, I think a
        pervading sense, during the 1950s of American’s postwar position in the world,
        of the—at that point, the bi-polar nature of the world. The events of the late
          1940s and early 1950s, you know, played a very large role in people’s
        vision of the world as being essentially an east and west division between the democracies
        in the west and at that point what was perceived to be the growing threat of, you know, the
        communist bloc, which covered most of eastern <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and
          <placeName>China</placeName>.During the early—I guess the late 1950s, another
        very strong influence on my generation, especially the young men in my generation, was the
        advent of the—you know, the development of the arms race, in which <placeName>the United
          States</placeName> and <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> and then eventually
        <placeName>Communist China</placeName> had each acquired nuclear weapons, had been involved
        in a series of proxy wars, whether these occurred, you know, in <placeName>Asia</placeName>
        or in <placeName>Africa</placeName> or in the western hemisphere.In
          <date when="1957">1957</date> I think probably the seminal event for the 1950s was the
        <name type="event">Russian launching of the Sputnik [1] satellite</name>, which suddenly placed <placeName>the United
          States</placeName> and individuals in <placeName>the United States</placeName> in a
        situation in which the Russians had the capability of launching an intercontinental nuclear
        missile that could land in your neighborhood. And I think that the presence of that threat
        was—was pervasive.I grew up in a situation in which—well, this is now mocked
          oday—you know, there were periodic drills at the local elementary schools,
        in which you would literally go to the halls, put your head against the wall, in
        anticipation of a nuclear blast.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">The “duck and cover.”</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Right, “duck and cover.” And this led—this sort of reached, I guess, its fever
        pitch in the early 1960s, and I guess probably, again, a—a—a point in history
        that you’re likely to be familiar with, <name type="event">the Cuban Missile Crisis</name>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I—I remember my—my father packing sandbags in our basement and putting away
        food and water in anticipation of a nuclear attack. I remember seeing—and, yeah, at this
        point I’m in my—in my early teens.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I remember seeing trucks rolling through the streets, on the main drag in
          <placeName>Uniondale</placeName>, moving troops to <placeName>Florida</placeName>. At that
        point, our community was adjacent to an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> base, which was
        extremely busy with troop movements. So there was a real sense of impending doom, I think
        probably more felt by my parents than by me and my contemporaries, but it was certainly a
        world in which there was an imminent threat of conflagration. And I think that certainly
        provided, you know, the sort of political context in which I grew up. I think it’s
        interesting that, you know, contrary to more, you know, current trends, there was a very
        strong hawkish element in both political parties, you know, during the largest proportion of
          the ’50s. <persName>Dwight [D.] Eisenhower</persName> was president, and, of
        course, he was a general and had been very much involved in <name type="event">the Second
          World War</name>.Interestingly enough, in the <name type="event">1960 presidential election</name>, one
        of the major elements of <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName>’s campaign was his promise to
        end the so-called “missile gap,” a perceived advantage of <placeName>the Soviet
          Union</placeName> over <placeName>the United States</placeName> in terms of, you know, the
        space program and the ability to deliver nuclear weapons through intercontinental ballistic
        missiles.So it was a very, you know, charged period in which there was a—a sense, certainly
        among young men in the working classes, that the country was threatened, that we, as our
        fathers had, would have an obligation to, you know, if necessary, fight to defend the
        country.It was also a period in which there was the draft, and every young male, when they
        reached the age of I think it was actually 17, had to register with the draft,
        and a large portion of, you know, each cohort of graduating high school seniors, at least
        the young men, would go into the military.And I think here it’s important, at least in terms
        of my own experience, to look at this from a perspective of class. You know, I grew up in a
        working-class community, and I think the sense in the working-class community was
        essentially that one had an obligation to serve. The vast majority of working-class young
        men did serve. That was I think in fairly—in fairly strong contrast to the experience you
        would have had in an upper-class community, where essentially your parents weren’t union
        laborers but were in a professional capacity or had a certain degree of, you know, economic
        comfort. I think it was easier for that—for those folks to go to college.There were
        exemptions for the draft if you were in college, and there were also ways in which one could
        avoid the draft if one had the necessary financial support. There were always ways out if
        you had money, not unlike the situation in <name type="event">the Civil War</name>, when you
        could essentially buy your way out of the draft.And so I think there were also significant
        class differences in—in that regard, although certainly, you know, part of my experience
        growing up was having an older cousin, whom I idealized—idolized, who had gone through
          <placeName>Yale [University]</placeName> on a <orgName>[U.S.]
          Navy</orgName> scholarship and become a naval officer. So I had sort of a—a model
        in my mind about a certain kind of route out of the working-class environment through
        service in the military. So that was, you know, part of the world that I lived in and part
        of the sensibility I had with regard to the role of the military in society and also
          <placeName>America</placeName>’s role in a bi-polar world, in which the threat of nuclear
        war was omnipresent.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Wow. So that’s—that’s a lot of stuff. I want to go back to a few things
        in there. Speaking about—you spoke a lot about the society and the societal sort of pressure
        and direction and the neighborhood as well, but can you tell me a little bit more about,
        like, you, personally, and your family? Within your household, what kind of pressures were
        there—were there pressures there to serve in the military? What was - as you got older, how
        did you speak within your household about <name type="event">the Cold War</name>?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, as I indicated, you know, earlier in our conversation, as essentially an
        accident of my background and based upon my father’s ethnicity and the ethnicity of his
        family, there was a very strong feeling of anti-communism in our family. We had
        had—essentially my father’s family in <placeName>Russia</placeName> were liquidated in
          the 1920s, and that was a very powerful sense of history that was part of our
        family and also part of the Russian ethnic community that we were—you know, that we lived
        within.I was brought up in the Russian Orthodox Church, and it was, at
        that time, as it has become again today, you know, primarily a church that
        served an immigrant community that had, you know, a similar perspective. There was a huge,
        you know, flow of immigrants from eastern Europe, you know, during
        the course of the 20th century, and a—a large portion of those, especially
        my—my grandparents on my father’s side, contemporaries—most of them had left
          <placeName>Russia</placeName> as a result of the end of the First <name
          type="event">World War</name> and the <orgName>Bolshevik</orgName> putsch and revolution, which resulted in a
        highly polarized society and one in which, you know, essentially under <persName>[Leon]
          Trotsky</persName>, during the <name type="event">civil war in Russia</name> and
        afterwards, there were liquidations of entire classes within what became <placeName>the
          Soviet Union</placeName>.And I think that was a very strong imprint in terms of the—of the
        world view I had. And, you know, essentially it shaped, within my family, what would
        be—essentially be a political attitude, which was one in which there was very little
        sympathy for, you know, the old Left. And I think that was, you know, part of what grew up
        in. My—my father was, you know, very anti-communist. He had had the experience during <name
          type="event">the Second World War</name> of working with Russian prisoners of war that had
        been taken prisoner towards the end of <name type="event">the Second World War</name>—And I
        don’t know how familiar you are with the history of <name type="event">the Second World
          War</name> in the east, but there were entire armies that were fighting for <placeName>the
          Soviet Union</placeName> that essentially went over to the side of the <orgName>Nazis</orgName> because they
        were so strongly anti-communist. And many of these—what—what—what—Russian soldiers who ended
        up fighting for the Germans were then captured by the Americans during the final
          months of the war and were brought to prison camps in <placeName>the United
          States</placeName>.My father was a Russian speaker, and he acted as an interpreter among
        these prisoners of war, and part of the stories that I heard when I was a kid were, you
        know, his experience with those soldiers who had essentially—you know, from the Soviet
        perspective—betrayed their country being forcefully repatriated to <placeName>the Soviet
          Union</placeName>, and they were all killed. [Laughs.] Right? So essentially there
        was—there was a sense of, you know, I guess polarity and also a sense that, you know, there
        were complex issues in the political situation that resulted in untoward, you know,
        experiences for certain people of my—my ethnic background on my father’s side.For my
        mother’s side of the family—again, in terms of, you know, personal context—my grandfather
        had the experience of, you know, coming through <name type="event">the First World
          War</name> wounded and then, you know, with the collapse of the—of the German army in
          <date when="1918">1918</date>, returning from <placeName>France</placeName>, where he had been in the
        trenches for three years, to a political situation in
          <placeName>Germany</placeName> in which there was <name type="event">civil war</name>, and there were—there was a
        very powerful, you know, communist revolution that went on in <placeName>Germany</placeName>
        that resulted in street fighting throughout the early 1920s, and essentially
        the breakdown of civil government within <placeName>Germany</placeName> and the
        establishment of, you know, Soviet or—or—or communal governments in a number of German
        cities and, again, periods of violent confrontation between returning veterans from the
        front and essentially, you know, communist agitators, and there was street fighting.So my
        grandfather had gone through this experience in the early ’20s of being a
        veteran, of being assaulted in the streets by communist activists because he was still in
        uniform, and then watching how that eventually settled into the—into the
          <orgName>Weimar [Republic] government</orgName>.And also he had the experience of
        watching the nascent period of <orgName>National Socialism [Nazism]</orgName> in
          <placeName>Germany</placeName> and all the issues that that raised, so there was a sense,
        I think, more in my family than in others, of, you know, European history and central
        European history placed within the context of the nuclear arms race, <name type="event">the Cuban Missile
        Crisis</name>—you know, a sense of anxiety and risk.I think another significant element, certainly
        for anyone my age, was the <name type="event">assassination of President Kennedy</name>, in which
        there were all kinds of unresolved issues as to how that had really occurred. I think
        there’s still debate about that today. But certainly, you know, the fact that
          <persName>Lee Harvey Oswald</persName> had essentially been in
          <placeName>Russia</placeName> for a number of years raised all kinds of
        suspicions about what was going on.It was also the tail end of the <persName>[Senator Joseph
          R.]
        McCarthy</persName> era, in which there was a very strong polarization in American
        politics between, you know, the left and the right. And this permeated lots of social
        discussions.So it was a period in which, you know, politics had a different kind of
        seriousness. I think we really haven’t experienced that recently until, you know, the
        post-<name type="event">9/11 [2001 attacks]</name> world, in which there was a sense of imminent threat,
        you know, to the average American in his home.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Yeah. So you had this strong background in the area, and obviously your
        family had very strong opinions in a certain direction. Was there pressure on you or did you
        feel the need, from that background, to serve in the military? You spoke about your older
        cousin, who went to <orgName>Yale</orgName> and ended up serving as well. Was that something
        that was kind of all around your family? Did a lot of your family end up serving?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, you know, I’m an only child, so I would say that certainly it—there was
        an expectation—and, again, I think this was primarily something that existed within the
        working-class community—that young men would serve in one capacity or another. I was never
        pressured into looking at the <orgName>military</orgName> as a career, nor was their a particular pressure from
        my—my parents for me to, you know, join the <orgName>Navy</orgName> in the way that I
        did.You know, my father was a fairly—you know, a fairly sophisticated fellow in terms of
        his—his understanding of the world. He spent five years in the
          <orgName>Army</orgName>, and, you know, he had a lot of ambivalent feelings about the
        <orgName>military</orgName>, you know. And, again, it was—it was just not so much within the context of my
        immediate family but in the context of our community, and in the way young men were—and boys
        were socialized. What you did as a young boy was you played war. You put on, you know, your
        dad’s old campaign cap or his, you know, set of <name type="event">World War II</name>
        fatigues. All young men—at least within my, you know, age group and peer group, you know,
        had toy guns, and you would get together with a bunch of your friends and go to the local
        woods and play war. It was just part of the way you were socialized.And I think, you know,
        one example of that is probably, you know, in the—in the motion picture, you know, Born on
          the Fourth of July. You’d see the <persName>Tom Cruise</persName> character
        as a young boy, growing up on <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, in the same context that I
        did. You know, that was part of the way you were socialized, is that, you know, the image of
        masculine—the masculine role model included <orgName>military</orgName> service because it was part of the
        world you lived in, and it was seen as a necessity to protect, you know, your—your
        particular way of life. It was a very—It was a period in which people were very much
        more—very patriotic. You know, people—you know, there were flags everywhere on the
          Fourth of July. From a young age, you were, you know, in some ways directed into
        what might be considered the paramilitary organizations of the <orgName>Cub Scouts</orgName> and the
          <orgName>Boy Scouts [of America]</orgName>. And, you know, I had been a <orgName>Cub
        Scout</orgName>, and I was a <orgName>Boy Scout</orgName>, you know, through my first couple
          of years in high school. You wore a uniform. You know, the <orgName>Boy
          Scouts</orgName> had begun, you know, in the—in <placeName>England</placeName> during the
        period of the <name type="event">[Second] Boer War</name> essentially as a—as a pre-military, you know, organization
        in which young men would learn to wear a uniform, to handle weapons, to live outdoors, to
        march. So there was a—there was a very strong, you know, feeling within the—within my peer
        group of young men that military service was a part of the world that you were living in and
        part of the role that you would play as a young man.I think there was a sense, a very strong
        sense of citizen soldiers. There was a feeling that everyone would serve in the <orgName>military</orgName> as
        part of your citizenship. So it was a very different atmosphere than oday and
        certainly isn’t an experience that my children have had.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right, yeah. And would you—so you’ve mentioned the—the societal, like, the
        working-class background. Was this—also, was this idea of the citizen soldier, the <orgName>military</orgName>
        service—was that institutionalized in the education system you went through at all?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I think—I think to some degree it was. Certainly, you know, this was the
        pre- —you know [chuckles], <persName>[Howard] Zinn</persName> era in—in the teaching of
        American history. And American history was, you know, in many ways taught as, you know, a
        series of armed struggles that created the nation. You know, you—you went back to the—you
        know, the foundations of <placeName>the United States</placeName> in the <name type="event">[American]
        Revolutionary War</name>. The notion of citizen soldiers, to some degree the idealization of
          <persName>George Washington</persName>. We were certainly taught, as part of the
          <orgName>New York State educational system</orgName> in public schools, about the
        history of the <name type="event">Revolutionary War</name> and all the, you know, wars that
        followed it. I think that an awful lot of history—well, an awful lot of American history was
        taught in terms of armed conflict, and armed conflict in creating the nation, both in its
        inception and then in terms of the acquisition of territory. Certainly with regard to the
        <name type="event">[American] Civil War</name>, you have to, again, put this back into context—when I was in, you
        know, elementary school and junior high school, it was the 100th anniversary of <name
          type="event">the Civil War</name>, and that was taught with a great deal of intensity, and
        it was all about service, whether it was for the North or the
        South.So I think there was an expectation. There was a pattern and
        there was a set of, you know, realities. You got your draft card at a certain age. You were
        classified based upon your physical capabilities. And there was an expectation that at some
        point or another, you would engage in public service. And I think it was very much a—an
        element of the identification of the male role in society, that you were going to be
        responsible, at some point, for, you know, potentially taking up arms and defending your
        country.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Wonderful.So that brings us to your decision to go to <placeName>Dartmouth
          College</placeName>. Can you speak a bit about that, just how you chose, out of all the
        places across this country, to come to a little, small school up here in the
          North?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I would, again, sort of relate it back to the experience I had with my
        cousin. Again, as an only child, he was essentially a big brother figure for me. And I
        remember when he was at <orgName>Yale</orgName>, you know, talking to him about his
        educational experience, about what <orgName>Yale</orgName> meant, and about, you know,
        college, at an early stage in my life.And one of the things he mentioned to me was that, you
        know—he said if he hadn’t gotten to <orgName>Yale</orgName>, he would have gone to
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. He thought <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was the kind of
        place where I might be happy. And that concept of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> as a place
        where I would feel comfortable and which also would offer a fine education was something
        that was reinforced as I entered my—my teen years, my early years in high
        school.I happened to have, you know, become acquainted with some men and women, young men
        and women who were somewhat older than I was, and they talked about school, and
         <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was always one of the schools that had been mentioned as a
        potential good place to go, especially for someone who was an athlete, someone who liked the
        out of doors, and <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was also identified as, interestingly enough,
        one of the more conservative environments within the—within <orgName>the Ivy
          League</orgName>. It was rural rather than urban. It had a very strong tradition of
        <orgName>military</orgName> involvement. Certainly, the <orgName>10th Mountain [Division]</orgName>—I mean, that’s part of
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>’s history.So I think it was a number of different
        suggestions, and then when I was a junior in high school, as is the case with most folks,
        even in those days, I got together with my parents and started talking about
        where I might go to college. And we visited a number of schools in the
          Northeast. I didn’t have any particular interest in going west,
        still rather a parochial vision of things. And in an experience I think shared by many, my
        parents took me to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and we pulled into
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, and I walked onto the <placeName>[Dartmouth]
        Green</placeName>, and fell in love with the place.And it was—it was sort of a no-brainer in some ways.
        It just seemed right. I applied Early Decision, and it was—happily enough, got accepted, so
        I didn’t apply to any other school, and nothing ever really presented itself as a
        significant alternative. I think that if I hadn’t gone to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I
        probably would have gone to<orgName> Amherst [College]</orgName> or
         <orgName> Williams [College] </orgName> because I think, you know, in conversations with
        my parents, the idealized notion of the small liberal arts college in <placeName>New
          England</placeName> was very attractive.And I think it was also—it also represented an
        opportunity to, you know, transcend, you know, the—the working-class world that I had grown
        up in, although both my parents were educated and my father had gone to college, but we were
        poor. And I think the <orgName>Ivy League</orgName> and <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> represented the ability—or
        the opportunity for, you know, a trans-class assimilation. You could go to
          <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and it would open doors to you, much in the way that my
        cousin had gone to <orgName>Yale</orgName> and had, you know, opportunities presented to
        him. It did seem to be a pathway.And, again, another element of the ’50s and ’60s, when I
        was educated, was the idealization of the American public school system as essentially an
        escalator that would allow talented youth to, you know, assume different class roles, to
        essentially become part of the professional class rather than a trade class.And it’s also
        particular to the nature of the ’50s and ’60s that—although, you know, I think much more
        controversial—if you were—when you were in a public school system, from the time you were in
        third or fourth grade, you were tested and tracked and put into essentially different
        classes and presented with different coursework based upon how you performed on a standard
        intelligence test. And I and a number of my contemporaries, in a working-class community,
        were fortunate enough to—to test well, and we were put into what was called the honors
        program.So from the time I was in fourth or fifth grade, I was in a class segment that
        received special opportunities and, you know, more challenging classes and was essentially,
        you know, pre-selected for the opportunity to go to college. And, again, I—I was a pretty
        good student, and I was sort of identified as one of a—of a cohort within my high school
        that would have the opportunity to go on to <orgName>the Ivy League</orgName> or—and I think
        this is also significant in terms of the world that I’m trying to conjure for you—go to one
        of the <orgName>military</orgName> academies.In the working-class community in which I grew up, the highest
        honor was going on to <placeName>[the U.S. Military Academy at] West Point</placeName> or
          <placeName>Annapolis [the U.S. Naval Academy]</placeName>, and the top
        students—the top student athletes were—you know, became familiar with the local congressmen,
        and the great opportunity would be to get an appointment to one of the <orgName>military</orgName> academies,
        and that was seen to be a success.When folks came back to the traditional Thanksgiving Day football game against our main rival, it was always a tradition
        for the returning graduates who were in the military academies to wear their uniforms at the
        football games and also for other graduates to come back in uniform. And, again, if you look
        up until about, you know, the—the mid ’60s, for a young man to appear in
        uniform, it was a symbol of honor, and, you know, young men who were in the military would
        wear their uniforms to church, and they would have obtained a certain amount of respect and
        position in the community through that service. So, again, it’s a very different world.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.So your decision, obviously, like a lot of what you just said—was there
        also—did it also consist of a—because I know you later joined the <orgName>NROTC
        [Naval Reserve Officers’ Training Corps]</orgName>. Was that factoring into your decision as well?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I—I actually joined the <orgName>NROTC</orgName>
        my senior year in high school.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And, again, it was <date when="1964-12">December of 1964</date>. For me, there was this
        pattern that my cousin had established in going through <orgName>Yale</orgName> on a
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> scholarship. And, given my parents’ economic situation, that also
        seemed like an avenue of possibility for me, so that in my senior year in high
        school, I took a <orgName>Navy</orgName> exam and did sufficiently well so that I was
        offered the opportunity to, while I was still in high school, to—to join the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName>, with the understanding that if I joined the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName>, the <orgName>Navy</orgName> would pay for my way through college,
        and then I would have a service obligation when I—you know, four years later.So
        when it came to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, I applied Early Decision and was accepted, and
        at the same time, I joined the <orgName>Navy</orgName> in order to be able to pay for
         <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so it was—you know, it was—it was part of the overall
        package. And it was an opportunity—it was an alternative to going to <placeName>West
          Point</placeName> or <placeName>Annapolis</placeName> or <placeName>the Air Force
          Academy</placeName>. In other words, you would be able to, you know,—you joined the
        military, you would become an officer, and they would put you through
          <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. And at that point, that was one of the major avenues through
        which working-class young men could obtain a college education and also an <orgName>Ivy League</orgName>
        education, because all the Ivies had, you know, <orgName>Navy</orgName> and
          <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC. And there was a significant chunk of the student body who
        were in the <orgName>military</orgName>. And it was just a way that, you know, you could—you could find your
        way into an <orgName>Ivy League</orgName> education without going tremendously into debt.</u>
      <u who="MANNES"><orgName>Gotcha</orgName>.Okay, so I’m going to come back to
          <orgName>NROTC</orgName> later, but I want to start with—so you told me your first
        impressions are that you end up falling in love with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and that
          <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is—was a source of comfort, in the end, for you. So what were
        your first impressions as a student?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I was—I was overwhelmed.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">In—in—in a number of different ways. I was very anxious about whether or not
        when I got on campus I could, you know, cut the mustard, as it were, whether I was, you
        know, a good enough student to be in <orgName>the Ivy League</orgName>—you know, because I
        was the first person from my high school to go to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. And so my
        freshman year I had—you know, had those sorts of anxieties. I remember getting back my first
        set of grades, freshman year, and getting some A’s and B’s and feeling, Oh, wow! I turned a
        cartwheel on the Green. I said, You know, maybe I can actually fit in here.So I was—I was
        immediately enamored of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I had a wonderful set of teachers. I
        enjoyed my peers. I had, you know, a very unalloyed, positive experience. One of the
        elements of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> that also was inescapable was the fact that you
        were living in a different world, because I was living in a different world than the one
        that I had grown up in, in terms of the—the educational situation.I remember—I played
        lacrosse at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> for four years, and I remember, you
        know, going to the first, you know, couple of practices, and each time—each day you went
        into practice, you got a fresh role. You got a fresh T-shirt, a fresh jock, a fresh pair of
        socks, all cleaned and pressed, and you went out on a playing field and the grass was, like,
        you know, two inches thick, and it was beautifully manicured.And when I was in high school,
        you didn’t get a role. You wore the same T-shirt through the entire season. You
        brought it in from home. The playing fields, you know, have rocks on them. You know, there
        wasn’t much grass. You know you were - it was a working-class, you know, community. It was
        a—you know, a different kind of environment.One of the things that, you know,
         <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was all about, you know, although I don’t think I would have
        labeled it that way, was certainly world of privilege. You know, life was pretty sweet at
         <placeName> Dartmouth</placeName>, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Beautiful. Everything was manicured. You know, you were surrounded by preppies.
        It was—you know, it was a very—it was an interesting, you know, transition. But it was also
        one that was very welcoming, and, again, <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in <date when="1965">1965</date>
        was a very different place than <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> is today or the
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> that my daughter experienced. She’s a <orgName>2012</orgName>. It
        was all men. It was virtually all white men, although, you know, there were some—there was a
        small minority population. And I think in my freshman class there were 126 high school
        football captains. So it was a jock-y place. And one of the ways that you—you know, you
        could find a place a <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was by playing sports. And everybody
        played intramurals, and a lot of—you know, I was a varsity athlete, you know, for
        four—for—for three years.In those days, <orgName>the Ivy
          League</orgName> had rules whereby as a freshman you couldn't play on a varsity team, so
        there were a bunch of freshman teams as well. So it was a very jock-y, outdoorsy kind of
        place in which I felt very comfortable because that was the—you know, the role that I had
        grown up in in high school. I was a jock, you know. I was in a high school fraternity
        [chuckles], believe that or not.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So there were—there were sort of—<placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—you know, it all
        seemed very accessible to me, and I found the educational experience absolutely wonderful
        and, you know, continue to feel that, at least, you know, based on my first-hand experience
        during that year, is that I got a tremendous education at
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and a significantly better one than my peers did at some
        other places. So I think that the—the emphasis on undergraduate education at
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was probably much more—more powerful in those
          days. <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> really felt more like <placeName>Amherst</placeName>
        or <placeName>Williams</placeName> than it did like <placeName>Yale</placeName> or
          <placeName>Harvard</placeName>. And I just—you know, my four years at
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> were, you know, in terms of an educational experience, quite
        wonderful.And also I was at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in a very interesting transitional
        period. My freshman year, I wore a beanie, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Right? And when you were freshman at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you wore
        your beanie and you did work for the upperclassmen. You were hazed. The entire freshman
        class were hazed, in a friendly sort of way, but it was—you were moving into a world that
        had much more similarity to the 1920s and 1930s than it would to
        the 1970s and 1980s. You were—in <date when="1965">1965</date> you were at the
        tail end of a set of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> traditions that ran back to <name
          type="event">the Civil War</name>. You know, no women, freshman beanie. You wore your
        beanie until you won—the freshman class won the tug-of-war against the sophomore class on
        the <placeName>Green</placeName>.You know, there was a tremendous amount of school spirit. It was magical. My
        freshman year at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was undefeated in football. They won the
        <placeName>Lambert[-Meadowlands]</placeName> Trophy as the top team in the East. They were
        rated, like, ninth nationally. And I remember going down at the end of my freshman autumn,
        hitchhiking down to <placeName>Princeton [University]</placeName> to watch
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, undefeated, beat <placeName>Princeton</placeName>,
        undefeated, to become the top team in the East.So there was a
        tremendous amount of school spirit. There was a tremendous sense of
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> as, you know, the place where a certain kind of young, white
        male could attain a—a—a position of—of—of dignity and prestige and opportunity in society.
        So it was a—it was kind of a, you know, Camelot-y kind of experience, but one that was
        very—initially very much tied to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> traditions.And it was a
        rougher set of traditions, right? The Hovey murals [based on a drinking
        song by <persName>Richard Hovey</persName>, <orgName>Class of 1885</orgName>] were still there. We
        still sang about <persName>Eleazar Wheelock</persName> and 500 gallons of <placeName>New
          England</placeName> rum. And, you know, the social life was very different, right? No
        women!</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So the social life was all based upon, you know, road trips to the Seven
        Sisters, so different world.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. No, it sounds idyllic, though. Can you—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">It was.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">I’m sorry?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">It was. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. And van you tell me—so—a bit about your—what did
        you decide to study?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, this sort of takes you back to <date when="1957">1957</date> and
          <name type="event">Sputnik</name>. Part of the experience of being a young man with an IQ over 85
        in the late ’50s and early ’60s is that every young man was going
        to be a scientist so that we could beat the Russians in the space race. So I came to
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> thinking that I would go into physics or perhaps math or some
        form of science, although I—you know, I was also very interested in English language and
        literature, and that’s really where my talents lay.So my freshman year, I
        took—you know, second semester—I took three semesters of math. I took physics. I took
        chemistry. I took, you know, English and German and French. I took naval science. One of the
        things that people don’t realize is that when you were in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, two
        out of your nine courses each year were in naval science, right? So you’re
        taking, you know, Introductory to Eastern Religion, you’re taking Advanced Differential
        Calculus, and you’re taking Naval Gunnery [chuckles] as one of your courses.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Different kind of world. So I came to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> thinking
        that I would go into the sciences, but by the time I had, you know, reached a C-minus level
        in—what was it?—Math 26 or whatever it was, in chemistry and in physics, it dawned on me
        that I didn’t have the brain power or at least that kind of brain power to be a scientist,
        although I—I also, you know, flirted with a geology major up until—I didn’t decide on my
        major until my fall semester of senior year. I had taken enough science and math and geology
        to be a geology major, or I had taken enough English literature to be an English major, and
        I finally decided my senior year that I would major in English rather than
        geology because primarily I didn’t want to miss the football season, and if I
        was going to stay in the geology major, I would have had to have spent the freshman—I mean
        the fall term of my senior year in <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>, studying
        volcanoes, and I decided I’d rather spend it in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">[unintelligible; 55:38].</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. Well, I’d like to come back—so you’ve spoken a lot about how it is kind
        of idyllic experience that you had at school. You enjoyed all your classes. You enjoyed the
        social life. What was the experience with the <orgName>Navy ROTC</orgName> program?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, it was a very interesting experience. I would say that by the time I had
        finished the summer after my freshman year—and, yet again, to put
        this into context, if you were in the—in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, especially if you were a regular <orgName> ROTC</orgName>
        student, you were in the service. I was an enlisted man in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. And
        whenever I wasn’t at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, I was in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, so
        that the summer—in each of the summers between—after my freshman, sophomore and
         junior year, I went into uniform and spent the summer going through naval
        training.And in my so-called third-class cruise, the summer after my
          freshman year, I was on an aircraft carrier for a month, and I was on
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> flight training up in <placeName>Brunswick,
         Maine</placeName>, flying in anti-submarine patrol ships for another
          three weeks. And I have to say, that was my first experience as an enlisted man in
        the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. I absolutely hated it. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, you were treated like—you know, it was not a pleasant experience,
        although it was a fascinating experience. You know, I have very mixed feelings about this.
        So it became pretty clear to me rather early on in my experience in the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> that I was not going to be a mili- — a career officer. And I
        realized, you know, I—I—I had made a commitment. You know, they were paying for my
        education. I wasn’t—I didn’t particularly enjoy marching around, but that was, you know,
        part of the world.And there were certainly elements, you know, throughout my <orgName>military</orgName>
        experience that in retrospect were unique and fascinating and challenging and intense in
        ways that few other things in my life have been. And part of my freshman year,
        I got to fly in an airplane for the second or third time in my life. You know, I was on an
        aircraft carrier, you know, eight decks down, you know, with a bunch of semi-educated
        enlisted men, you know, who would—you know, you could get mugged in the aircraft carrier (it
        was such a large, you know, world unto itself). It was fascinating, but it wasn’t, you know
        —I didn’t—felt that this resonated within my soul, was something that would be my calling
        for the rest of my life.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. And how about at school. What did the program consist of?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, again, back through the time tunnel. Where you know have <placeName>Collis
          [Center for Student Involvement]</placeName>—that was the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> building.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Huh!</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And you would take your classes—they had, you know, <orgName>Navy
        ROTC</orgName>, <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC, I guess <orgName>Army</orgName>,
        <orgName>Navy</orgName>—I don’t think they had <orgName>Air Force</orgName>; they may have
        had a small <orgName>Air Force</orgName> unit. Each—I took two classes each year of naval
        science, which were taught, you know, on campus, and it would be, you know, Naval
          Gunnery, Navigation, you know, Naval
          History. You would—so you have—you know, two out of your nine courses would be
        in “naval science” (in quotes). There were a bunch of naval officers on campus who were a
        part of the faculty, if you can imagine that. And every week, every
          Wednesday afternoon, you would have drill, in which ca- —in which event all
        the ROTC guys, whether you were in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> or the
          <orgName>Army</orgName>, would put their uniforms on and go to the—you know, to the
        football field, behind—you know, behind the varsity house, and you would march. We were all
        issued <name type="event">World War I</name>-era
        <placeName>Springfield</placeName> rifles, and we’d put our uniforms on and march around,
        you know, and do drill, you know, on Wednesday afternoons.And fortunately,
        since I was an athlete, if you were on a—on a—on an athletic team, you were forgiven drill,
        so I only had to drill in the autumn because in the winter and the spring I had
        lacrosse practice. But you know, in the—in the autumn, every Wednesday
        afternoon, I’d put on this itchy, wool <orgName>Navy</orgName> uniform and go out under the
        football field and march around with a rifle. You can imagine that.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. So how did this experience—how was this experience as a college student,
        especially as an undergraduate at a liberal arts education, where you’re sort of
        taught—you’re kind of on your own for the first time—you’re taught how to think for
        yourself? What is the comparison between that and being in the—in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, where you have
        people telling you what to do, and you kind of are being ordered around? Is there any sort
        of—did that come up at all? Did you ever think about that?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, I think—I think you just recognize that as part of the deal. First of
        all, you’re amidst all your peers, right? Everybody else is marching with you—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—in also a Dart- —right? And we were—you know, all of us who were regular—and
        they were regular in contract. There were people who were—you know, who had joined the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> and were in, and there were also students who were just kind
        of—you know, who were—there were guys who didn’t get scholarships, who were also in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>.
        You know, maybe it’s a strategy for avoiding the draft, whatever. But, you know, there was—I
        don’t think there was a sense among us, you know, that this was something strange and odd
        and that it somehow impinged upon our, you know, intellectual opportunities or curiosity. It
        was, you know, it was part of, you know, the world you were—you were—you were in. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right .</u>
      <u who="COOKE">It was part of fulfilling an obligation. It was no different in some ways than,
        you know, putting on your—your pads and picking up your lacrosse stick and going out to
          <placeName>Leverone [Field House]</placeName> and, you know, scrimmaging,
        right? They were both uniforms. Both times, you’re carrying a weapon, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">One form of combat a bit more stylized than the other, but if you think about
        what lacrosse is, it’s all about, you know, Indian tribes fighting for their women, right?
        So if there’s—it was part of a—of a role model. And there was also a—a—a tradition, and a
        fairly strong tradition, of <orgName>military</orgName> service as an emblem of—you know, the fulfillment
        of—of—of a societal obligation at the highest level. Let’s look at who the idealized
        individuals were in society, and, again, it’s sort of ancient history for you, but, you
        know, part of why <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> was so idealized was because of
        <name type="event">PT-109 [Motor Torpedo Boat]</name>. He was a naval officer, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">He was a naval—in quotes—“a naval hero,” and he had gone to
          <placeName>Harvard</placeName>, and, you know, he was [unintelligible; 1:04:04] into
          Camelot. So there was this notion, and I think it gets into the
        subtlety of differentiation among the <orgName>military</orgName> services, but there was always a sense that,
        you know, what you were as a naval officer was an officer and a gentleman. So there was a
        whole—there was a—there was a very strong social stratum associated with being a naval
        officer, and the fact that that was training for leadership of the country, and, you know,
        you looked at, you know, the history of—of—of <placeName>America</placeName>. They were
        <orgName>military</orgName> officers who ran this country and made it great, in many cases.So there was a
        different sense, I think, of the role of <orgName>military</orgName> service and a very strong sense that part
        of being in the ruling class was having had the experience of being a citizen soldier. And,
        you know, essentially it—it—it revolved around a certain image, again idealized image, of
        the role of the—of a man in society, as a leader, bearing social responsibility to protect
        the homeland in a polarized world, so that if you have this again, this kind of image of the
        <orgName>military</orgName> officer in <date when="1964">1964</date> and <date when="1965">1965</date>.And I think that in terms of the oral history
        you’re working on, there’s an immense change in the four years that I’m at
         <placeName> Dartmouth College</placeName> between the world of <date when="1965">1965</date>, when I had my
        beanie and I came on campus and I joined <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, and <date when="1969">1969</date>, when I graduated. So
        that—that—that four-year period was a period of very significant change, but I
        think it’s helpful to understand the vision that existed, you know, in the pre- —let’s call
        it the pre-<name type="event">Vietnam</name> era of the male officer and the role of the
        citizen soldier in the leadership of society and the sense that, you know, part of being a
        young man at an <orgName>Ivy League</orgName> school was the notion that at some point you might well
        serve.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So it was very—it—it—it was very much a part of the—of the world of
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. It was very much institutionalized at
         <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> at the beginning of this period, <date when="1965">1965</date>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Did you feel that this image of the citizen soldier was also shared
        by—you mentioned earlier there were the—there was also a large presence of, like, the
        preppy, like, maybe—like, upper-class, so to speak, population. Did they share this idea as
        well?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I think so. I think—I think that—well, I—I think it was pervasive. Now, I can’t
        speak to that segment, right? </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Because I came from a very different background, but I—I—I think that, you
        know, that was part of a world view, and I think there was probably also—there might also
        well have been traditions, say, if you were an <placeName>Andover</placeName> or an <placeName>Exeter</placeName> [a student at
          <placeName>Phillips Academy Andover</placeName> or <placeName>Phillips Exeter Academy</placeName>]
        or a <placeName>Choate [Rosemary Hall]</placeName> graduate, you know, about perhaps taking that kind of a role. I
        think an interesting example of this would be <persName>John [F.] Kerry</persName>, our
        current, you know, secretary of state. You know, I think he’s <placeName>Andover</placeName>, a <orgName>Yalie</orgName>. Joined the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> and, you know, essentially went into the then-current version of a
        <orgName>PT-109</orgName>, to follow in that—that <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> path.So I think that,
        you know, while the—the impetus to go into <orgName>ROTC</orgName> or to get—you know, to—to—to join the
        <orgName>military</orgName> as essentially a class escalator was certain much more prominent among those of us
        who came from a less affluent background. I think that the—the—the division of the male
        elitist role model of citizen soldier was probably something that was also shared within,
        you know, the—the upper classes, those who—you know, those folks who—or some of those folks
        who came from money. And I think it was in a lot of the—let’s call them the
          WASP [White Anglo-Saxon Protestant] upper-class cohorts—you know, the
        65 percent of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> who went to prep school at that point.There were
        probably similar kinds of traditions of service, and I imagine that if you went to most of
        the prep schools that have, you know, 19th- and 18th-century foundations,
        somewhere in the chapel there is a—a—a marble slab with the names of dead graduates who died
        in the wars.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, I don’t know whether you’ve ever been to <placeName>Harvard</placeName>,
        but If you go into <placeName>Memorial Hall at Harvard</placeName>, it was built, you know, as a
        memorial to all the <placeName>Harvard </placeName>guys who died in <name type="event">the Civil
          War</name>, and that was very much a part of their world. And most <orgName>Ivy League</orgName> schools in
        their chapel had the names of dead graduates, graduates who died defending our country. So
        that was part of the—the ethos of these institutions as conduits to leadership roles in the
        country. I think there was a sense of service in that regard.And you certainly see it—you
        know, it was certainly there—again, when—when I was in my summer cruises with other <orgName>ROTC</orgName>
        students, there were the guys from <placeName>Yale</placeName>, there were the guys from
          <placeName>Harvard</placeName>, right?—all of whom had gone into a—a—a—similar kind of a—of an
        environment where, in the ’50s—in the ’40s and ’50s and the
          early ’60s there was this notion of a—a pathway through your late adolescence into
        maturity that involved a certain kind of public service, and that public service was
        primarily in the <orgName>military</orgName>, although certainly in my generation, thanks to, you know, the
          Kennedys, you also had the alternative of the <orgName> Peace
          Corps</orgName>. And the <orgName>Peace Corps</orgName> became sort of this other way of,
        you know, engaging in public service, and it was also an option to get out of the draft,
        right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So I think you have to realize that for most of my contemporaries, you had—you
        were going to have to do something when you got out of college. And either you were going to
        go in the military or you were going to find some way out of the military, and there were
        different sets of alternatives for that.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. So—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">David, I’m going to put you on hold for about two seconds
        here.Hi, I’ve returned. Are you still there?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah, still here.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Let’s continue.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So, yeah, no, I just—let’s get back into—what was the extracurricular life at 
         <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>? You spoke briefly about it, and you can feel free to bring
        in lacrosse as well here. I’m sure that factored in.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, extracurricular life. You know,—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Take that how you will. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Let’s see, if you flip back into my yearbook, what’s listed? I was in
          <orgName>Alpha Chi [Alpha]</orgName>, and I, you know, enjoyed my fraternity experience.
        I played lacrosse, and I was in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. [Chuckles.] And I was an usher at the
         <placeName> Episcopal Church of St. Thomas [sic; St. Thomas Episcopal
          Church]</placeName>. So what did I do extracurricularly?You know, lacrosse took up, you
        know, two of the three, you know, trimesters, so I was busy, you know, certainly in
          the spring—practice every day and traveling. In the winter I
        think we practiced also every day in the field house, so a lot of time with
          sports.<orgName>ROTC</orgName>—you know, when I wasn’t, you know, playing sports, you
        know, at least one afternoon a week, in which I’d be marching around carrying a rifle
        [chuckles], I was very much interested in other things that were going on on campus. You
        know, I enjoyed the <orgName>[Dartmouth] Film Society</orgName>. I wrote for <orgName>The D [The Dartmouth]</orgName>.But I also
        spent a lot of my time trying to have a social life [chuckles], which in those
          days meant road trips or dealing with mixers. I mean, it was a very different
        world, in which, you know, girls were not part of the scene, a different <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, in some
        ways a much more relaxed <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> because you didn’t have this whole
        world of, you know, hooking up and—and trying to figure out relationships in
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName>. What you do was either you had a hometown honey, who came
        up, you know, for <name type="event">Green Key [Weekend]</name> or <name type="event">[Winter] Carnival</name> or for,
        you know, <name type="event">Homecoming</name>, or you tried to find a friend, you know, somewhere within 150 miles of
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.You know, my freshman year we had something called the
        [Dartmouth College] Green Book. I don’t know if they still have it. But it’s where—you know,
        pictures of all the kids in the—in your freshman class, sort of like the ur Facebook. And at
        the end of the Green Book there were—there was a map of New England
        with the distance to travel to each of the women’s colleges within 120 miles, right?So on
          a typical weekend, either there would be something going on on campus and you
        would be busing girls in from <placeName>Skidmore [College]</placeName> or <placeName>Smith [College]</placeName> or
        <placeName>[Mount] Holyoke [College]</placeName>, or you’d try to find a buddy who had a car, and you’d go on a
        road trip. That was sort of what social life was all about. And it revolved around road
        tripping and also the fraternity system.And also the dorms. I mean, again, in the pre- —in
        the all-male <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you didn’t have, you know, the D-Plan, and you
        didn’t have this, you know, perpetual rescrambling of your world every semester. I mean,
        you—you tended to spend the first three years of your experience in the same
        dorm. So I spent my first three years in <placeName>Middle Fayerweather [Hall]</placeName>, and there
        was a very happy social life in <placeName>Middle Fayerweather</placeName> that was blended
        with folks.You played—you know, everyone was involved in intramurals, playing for your—for
        your dorm, so there was a social life around—around the dorms and a sense of identity as
        being someone from <placeName>Middle Mass [Massachusetts
          Row]</placeName> or <placeName>Fayer</placeName> or one of the other dorms. God help you if you were in the <placeName>Choates [the Choate
        Cluster]</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So—but there was, you know, a very active social world but one in which, again,
        there was tremendous change. My freshman year, we had parietals, which meant
        that during the week, women had to be out of the dorms at eight o’clock. On
          Friday night, a woman could be in the dorm until eleven o’clock, and on
          Saturday night, women could be in the dorms until one o’clock in the morning.
        No woman could be above the first floor of a fraternity house. And if you went down to
          <placeName>Smith</placeName> or <placeName>Holyoke</placeName>, right, and had a date, you
        had to get them back to their—their dorm room by one, and there would be a house mother
        there [chuckles], right? So it was a very much more protective environment, much less, I
        think,—certainly no hooking up—in most—I think most—again, a different world here. Most of
        my contemporaries were probably virgins when they got to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and a
        lot of them probably left as virgins. Contraception at—my freshman year, it was
        prophylactics. You know, the [birth control] pill didn’t happen until well into my
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> experience, so there’s a whole nature of social
        interaction—was different.That being said, there was always something to do on campus, and
        there was just so much more, you know, campus spirit, I think. You know, it was a much more
        sort of vigorous kind of place than it is today. And I think the perfect
        example of that is <name type="event">Winter Carnival</name>. You know, in he four
          years that I was <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, the
        highlight of <name type="event">Winter Carnival</name> was the ski jump, right? And they had a ski
        jump out on the golf course, where guys—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—would jump off of a ski jump, right? And guys would go out there, you know,
        and put on a pair of skis and go down this thing and fly into the air. Now, of course,
        everybody would just—you know, that’s—that’s history. And when you built, you know, a <name type="event">Winter
        Carnival</name> statue, everybody went out and built it. y senior year, we had a
        giant dragon with a—a—a propane torch in its mouth that spewed flames [chuckles], you know?
        And it was, like, 80 feet high.And—and we built the bonfire by ourselves. You know, we
        didn’t have some guy truck—you know, you did everything yourselves, in large part because
        you didn’t have anything else to do, right? It’s 3,000 guys in the woods, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So there was much more, you know, sort of active engagement in that regard.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Again, very superficial in terms of extracurricular activities. I also have to
        say I was a very serious student. I—I came to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> terrified that I
        wasn’t going to be able to hack it, and I was a—you know, I was a serious student. I wanted
        to—by the time I graduated, I wanted to go on and—and be an academic, so I felt that, you
        know, I really—I enjoyed my courses. I had a terrific set of professors. And, to be quite
        honest, I would have loved to have stayed at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> for another
          two years and just taken more courses, I found the educational experience so
        wonderful in that regard. And I was kind of pissed that I had to go in the military, I must
        admit.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. Did—so you spoke—we’ve spoken a lot about the
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> experience and how it is kind of separate from the world. Was
        it removed from <name type="event">the Cold War</name>, or was—or was that still pervasive
        around campus?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I—I think—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And you certainly had a different experience in that, being in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> [spelling
        out the letters], in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> [pronouncing it ROT-C], and you would have felt that, but I guess
        the general atmosphere is what I’m asking about.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I think, again, you have to imagine a <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> campus
        in which it is commonplace and part of the society to have your peers, 10 percent of your
        peers, 15 percent of your peers in uniform, marching up and down the street, right? And if
        you were in a fraternity, and most guys were, a certain percentage of your fraternity
        brothers would be in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. It was just—it was—it was part of that—that blend of life. And,
        again, much more so in an accepted kind of way in the early days of my four
          years than towards the end, where there was, you know, a major kind of shift.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Sorry. Are you still there?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yeah, I’m still here. Yes, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. I just couldn’t see.So I want to—I want to talk a little bit about
          <date when="1968">the year 1968</date>, because there’s a lot of things that happened that year that
        kind of—I think, at least—started to make <name type="event">the Vietnam [War]</name> into a
        more national—I don’t know if “national story” is the right word, but certain things that
        just kind of drove the country into a new era, such as the Tet—there’s the <name type="event">Tet Offensive</name>,
          <name type="event">MLK [the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.] is
        assassinated</name>, <name type="event">RFK [Robert F. Kennedy] is
        assassinated</name>, there’s the <name type="event">Mỹ Lai Massacre</name>, there’s the <name type="event">antiwar protests at the
          Democratic National Convention</name>. Is that—does any of that factor in the
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—did that start changing anything?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Oh, of course. I—I—I think you—you know, there was a tremendous sea change
        at—at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and I don’t think it—it—it certainly began before
        <date when="1968">1968</date>—it might have reached a climax in <date when="1968">1968</date>, but, you know, you certainly have
        a—a—a—a societal change is going on, and I think that it tracks through both the polit-
        —national politics, the politics of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> and the way
        society was—the way education was being handled. And I think—you know, again, let me sort of
        track a parallel evolution. I spoke a little bit earlier about my freshman year, about
        parietals, right?—that you couldn't have women in the dorms, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">By my senior year, all that had gone, and people were cohabiting,
        right? They had already had the first co-ed weekends. You know, <persName>[Mary
          L.] “Meryl” Streep</persName> had come up and spent some time as a—as a student. There
        were tremendous social changes during that period of time. And there were—and—and—within
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, although <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was always a much more
        insular environment. It was—it was away from the center of the student unrest, which really
        grew out, you know, primarily of <placeName>[the University of California,]
          Berkeley</placeName> and then, you know, at some of the—at the urban
        universities, primarily <placeName>Harvard</placeName>. That all sort of resonates into
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName> but at some kind of a remove.You get to <date when="1968">1968</date>,
        and <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> is right in the middle of it, right? Because you have
          <persName>Malcolm X</persName> coming to the campus. You have <persName>George
        [C.] Wallace [Jr.]</persName> coming to the campus. You are certainly in the midst of seeing <name
          type="event">the Vietnam War</name> on television. You have guys that you knew as a
        freshman getting killed in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, right?—guys that you were in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>
        with—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">They’re already dead at this point, right? So—and there—there is also a sense
        that with <name type="event">Tet</name> and with, you know, the—I guess the popularization, the
        immediacy of the news coverage of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, you’re in the
        midst of this. And there’s also a growing realization between <date when="1964">1964</date> or <date when="1965">’65</date> and
          <date when="1968">’68</date> that suddenly, instead of having 65,000 troops in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you’ve got a million or 500,000, 750,000 kids, ages 17 to
        21, your contemporaries, who are now in the rice paddies, right? And for those of us who
        came from a working-class background, our high school classmates who didn’t go to college,
        who got drafted, are all in country now. And of my—the close—there was, like, seven of
        us—there were seven close friends of mine that I grew up in high school with, who were sort
        of a little gang. And four of us went in the military. I went in late. Three of my friends
        had already gotten drafted and were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, right? So suddenly
        this becomes much less theoretical.And also, you know, again, <date when="1964">1964</date>,
          <date when="1964-12">December of ’64</date> or the beginning of 1965, when I go into <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, nobody ever
        dreamed that <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> would extend for that long a period
        of time. So suddenly this is all sort of changing. Suddenly, with—really in <date when="1966">’66</date>, <date when="1967">’67</date>,
        there’s a huge buildup of an American military presence in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>,
        and there is the increasing realization on the part of my peer group—right?—my cohort that,
        Shit, I could get killed over there! Right?And this isn't<name type="event"> World War
          II</name>. Not necessarily winning. So there’s a—there’s a tremendous sense of angst that
        comes onto campus, and it ties into a lot of other social changes, primarily driven by the
        civil rights movement, right? And all kinds of horrors happened, right? You’ve got
          <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> getting shot. You know, there—there is suddenly a
        much more intrusive effect of the outside world on the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>
        community.And one of the ways you feel it, one of the ways I felt it as someone in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> is
        suddenly <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> ends up being visited by traveling circuses of outside
        political agitators, which is a very important part of trying to understand what happened in
          <date when="1968">1968</date> on the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> campus, is that there were groups of
        young people, who went from campus to campus across <placeName>America</placeName>, staging
        antiwar demonstrations.And they would essentially come into—they would arrive, you know, on
        a Thursday afternoon in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, right? A convoy of cars
        would come up from <placeName>New Haven [Connecticut]</placeName> or
        from <placeName>Boston [Massachusetts]</placeName>, and suddenly
        there would be demonstrators on campus you’d never seen before, who would then, you know,
        attract like-minded members of the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> community, and suddenly
        there was a very different presence within <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, within what had
        been more or less the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> bubble. You start having outside
        agitators coming to campus.And also—you know, it’s also part of the surrounding world and
        society. And you’ve got a lot of guys, you know, especially guys who came from backgrounds
        of privilege, suddenly facing the fact that shit, I may actually have to do something like
        this, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And I think there was a lot of feeling on the part of certain elements that
        you’ve got to get this thing over with or else I’m going to get drafted, right? So a—a chill
        comes on the campus, and with it, you know, <placeName>Dartmout</placeName>h sort of gets pulled
        into this larger student movement by having groups of students and not-students coming onto
        campus and agitating.So the—the—the—the little pastoral world of
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName> during this four-year period, maybe it—maybe
        it peaks in <date when="1968">’68</date> and <date when="1969">’69</date>—suddenly the world changes a little bit, and you’ve got
        demonstrations on campus. You know, I think the majority of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>
        students are still part of that world that they were in when they got there, but certainly
        there are—the outside world intrudes in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> in a way that it
        hadn’t so much before.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.And so what are your—can I ask you what were your personal thoughts on
        the anti-war protesters or agitators is the word you used?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I think, you know, having been sat upon, I was not particularly, you
        know,—I didn’t have particularly warm feelings toward them, particularly with regard to the
        guys that weren’t from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, right? I mean,
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was a pretty insular place. I know—I certainly had no problem
        with my peers, you know, having different political views about the war. I think by the time
        you get into—by the time <name type="event">Tet</name> has gone through, you realize that this is pretty much of a
        mess, right?—that there—that this might have been a terribly bad idea.You know, at the same
        time, you know, you’re in a situation that—at least in my case—you know, you’ve made a
        commitment; you’re in the <orgName>military</orgName> right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">If you drop out of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you go into the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName> for four years as an enlisted man. And you’re in, you
        know. That’s it. You got a crew cut.
          You’ve—you’ve—you’ve made a
        commitment. What are your alternatives? <placeName>Canada</placeName>?
          <placeName>Sweden</placeName>? So that—you’ve sort of—you’ve gone into this in one world,
        and now you’re living with the consequences of that in the second world.I think that—I would
        say—again, maybe this is just from my perspective—I would say that 85, 90
        percent of the—of the students at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> were either ambivalent or
        opposed to the antiwar agitators or those on the campus who acted out. But there was also
        sympathy, you know. I think my—you know, two of my best friends from high school, you know,
        did whatever they could to stay out the military. And that—you know, it was real. I mean,
        you—you work in a—certainly, I personally was not in a position of condemning someone
        because they didn’t want to go to—go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, right? You know, it
        was not—you know, I had seen—at this point, I had had high school buddies of mine killed
        there, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And there were <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> guys getting killed there that I
        knew from <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. And that’s a pretty chilling experience. So I think they’d know there was a
        lot of ambiguous [unintelligible; 1:31;53], but also I think, you know, maybe sort of a
        parochial feeling on the part of a lot of students that, you know, these guys—these aren’t
        Dartmouth people. These are people from God knows where, you know. And if you look at a lot
        of the contemporary imagery and you look at the people, you know, wearing sort of grotesque
        parodies of military uniforms, none of those folks were from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>.
        They were from out of town. And there was a sense that, you know, God, what are they trying
        to make this? They’re trying to make <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> into
          <placeName>Harvard</placeName>? Are they trying to make this into <placeName>Columbia
            [University]</placeName>? Are they trying to make this into <placeName>Berkeley</placeName>? It just
        wasn’t really part of, you know, what the majority of students were feeling, although,
        listen, everybody at this point, or virtually everybody had a draft card in their wallet
        that was going to send them into the military when they graduated.So this suddenly became
        personal in a different kind of way, and I think it—it forced a lot of people to—to think
        about things that they wouldn’t have otherwise. And, again, I—I talked a lot earlier in our
        conversation about class differences. I think this is also an area in which class
        differences made a—really became prevalent because I think there was a sense, basically—and
        this was part of something that was a larger sense of dislocation in the country—that if you
        came from money, you could get out of it. And there were lots of guys running off to their
        mom’s or their dad’s psychologists and getting, you know, “psych outs.” [Chuckles.] Or
        joining the <orgName>Peace Corps</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right, yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Or becoming high school teachers or whatever, or trying to go to grad school.
        There were always outs if you had money, but if you were some poor working-class slob,
        you’re goin’ in. So there were—there were—there was a lot of class tension there. But there
        was also a lot of, you know, individual soul searching about, Gee,
        what’s gonna happen a year from now when I graduate? Am I gonna get drafted?
          Jesus! I don’t wanna—you know. And especially if you get drafted into
        some war which is suddenly being portrayed in a way that’s very different from the east-west
        vision of the world that you had when you were a kid, right? This isn't<name type="event">
          World War II</name>. This isn’t defending <placeName>America</placeName> against the
        <orgName>Nazis</orgName>. It’s getting involved in some kind of a neo-colonial fight in a foreign country where
        it’s not very clear why we’re there or whether this is worth dying for.So there was—it was a
        real sea change, and there was also a lot of stuff just—you know, it was a very tumultuous
        time in the country. And, again, you’re up in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> a year, and
        you’re in the ivory tower, and yet I had buddies at <placeName>[John] Hopkins [University]</placeName> in <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
        in <date when="1968">1968</date>, where tanks came into the city to quell the rioting after
          <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> was assassinated.So there’s all kinds of, you
        know, pardon my French, shit breaking out across the—across the country. There were riots in
          <placeName>Chicago</placeName> in the—at <name type="event">the Democratic
          Convention</name>. There’s a sense of dislocation in society and a—a real, you know, sense
        that the world of the ’50s and ’60s was coming to an end and there was a
        radical change going on.And it’s also very important to put this into sort of a---a social
        context and an intellectual context, because one of the other things that’s happening
          <date when="1965">between 1965</date> and <date when="1968">1968</date>—and brace yourself for this—is the
          Beatles and the change in American music. There is a huge, huge
        explosion of contemporary culture in terms of where rock music is going at this point, and
        part of that social change is an underlying, you know, social activism. You’ve got
          <persName>Bob Dylan</persName> singing songs. You’ve got Peter,
          Paul and Mary singing songs. You’ve got
        Creedence Clearwater [Revival] singing songs. You have—you know,
        oodstock [Music &amp; Art Festival] is on the—is on the horizon. You have a huge youth
        social movement among the baby boomers, where the old constraints of society are being set
        aside. People—no more beanies. [Laughs.] Right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">No more tug-of-war between the freshman class and the sophomore class. There’s
        a –you’re—you’re--<placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> is like this little bubble of a—of an ivory
        tower floating in this now very—you know, very tempestuous seas of social change, and it
        does come onto campus, and you do have—you know, when <persName>George Wallace</persName>
        came to campus, there was a riot. The rioters weren’t <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> students,
        by and large, although we had—you know, <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> had, you know, had a
        <orgName>Students for a Democratic Society</orgName> group, and you’d probably be—your
        contemporaries will be speaking with some of that group. And there were about, you know,
        maybe 20 guys who are, you know, part of the <orgName>SDS</orgName>. And, of course, the
          <orgName>SDS</orgName>, <orgName>Students for a Democratic Society</orgName>, was a
        pan-campus organization, so when you talk about outside agitators coming in, you know, it’s
        the five guys at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> who are in <orgName>SDS</orgName> bringing in
        their buddies from <placeName>Northampton</placeName> or <placeName>Amherst</placeName>, for the
        traveling <orgName>SDS</orgName> circus onto campus. And they literally went from campus to
        campus and organized, you know, demonstrations. So they were outside agitators. It’s not
        that they weren’t guys at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> who had sympathies for them.But,
        again, my perception and perhaps a skewed one, given my background, which I’ve been very,
        you know, open about—I’d say 5 percent of the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> population, you
        know? And then you look at that bunch and, yeah, you know, there’s a lot of ego tripping
        going on. You know, I think that—you know, I think that when—when <name type="event">Parkhurst
          Hall was—was occupied</name>, it was about 12 guys, and the rest of the campus is
        outside sort of, you know, drinking beer and—and waiting for the police to come and throw
        them out. You know, they thought they were a bunch of, you know, egotistical assholes who
        were, you know, on an ego trip.And if you take a look at the imagery of the time, you see
        them smoking a cigar with their—with their feet up on a ohn—you know,
          <persName>John [S.] Dickey</persName>’s <orgName>[Class of 1929]</orgName>, you know, desk in
          <placeName>Parkhurst</placeName>. It was an ego trip. But, you know, in the end it was
        sort of like a snowball fight [chuckles], you know, or an all-campus water fight. I mean, it
        was something that happened.Suddenly you’ll have the—you know, <orgName>the New Hampshire
          State Police</orgName> come in with Belgian shepherds [sic; Belgian malinoises or German
        shepherds] that were, like, the biggest dogs I’ve ever seen. You know, it was certainly a
        happening, but it wasn’t necessarily a happening that—that came to
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> internally; it was something that sort of came to
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> from the outside. But it was also part of a much larger
        intrusion of the world into the bubble of what <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, you know, so
        often is, as a small college in the middle of nowhere.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.So—sorry, did I interrupt you?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">No, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So I—yeah. So this idea of the citizen soldier as, like, an ideal, it sounds
        like is really changing this time, and I know <orgName>ROTC</orgName> was later ended at
         <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, so what was—what was your experience as we move from
          <date when="1968">’68</date> and <date when="1969">’69</date> and towards your graduation, the campus climate
        about <orgName>ROTC</orgName> and your relationship with other students regarding this? Was there any tension
        there for you?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I think that it was certainly a huge transition for me, personally,
        right? You know, as I mentioned early on in my experience as a—as a midshipman, it became
        clear to me that I was not cut out to be in the <orgName>military</orgName>, you know, in terms of a career or
        a world. And I didn’t like people giving me orders. I wasn’t particularly excited about
        getting killed. I wasn’t feeling particularly gung-ho about, you know, ending up in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, although I did.In terms of the atmosphere on campus among
        my peers, I never felt, with regard to my fraternity, with regard to my teammates and with
        regard to most of my—virtually all of my friends at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> anything
        other than support for where I was as being in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>.Where I felt under attack was in
        situations in which people from outside of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> came to
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in order to make a demonstration and to have us, as those in
        <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, become the target of a—of a political demonstration that had nothing to do with us as
        individuals but had to do with us as symbols of the military in society. And indeed you are
        a symbol in that case. You’re wearing a uniform. You become a symbol of the
        military-industrial complex. You become a symbol of American imperialism. You become a
        symbol of cultural and—and—and racial dominance, right? There’s all kinds of—you become an
        easy target because you’re wearing—because you are a target. You’re wearing—you are living
        in a—in a—in an image of a certain kind of world.And certainly, by the time I’m graduating
        from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, no one is wearing a uniform to church anymore. No one is
        wearing a uniform in public because you become a target for all kinds of anxieties and
        antipathies that are going on in a—in a—in a period—a very turbulent period in American
        society that has to do with race, with gender and with, you know, political philosophy. It’s
        a very tumultuous period of time. And [to the extent? 1:42:08] you’re in the military, you
        become, you know, a—a symbol of this as soon as you put that uniform on. So none of the guys
        in ROTC wore uniforms anymore, and one of the things you have to deal with is the fact
        you’re the only guy in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> with a crew cut. [Laughs.] Right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So there are lots of changes. But I have to say that during that period of
        time, I never felt anything other than support and, you know, brotherhood from my fellow
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> students, with a very small exception of—you know, there was
        certainly a group of students who had a different political agenda, largely came from a
        different political background and experience than I did, and they were part of the society,
        and they were also, you know, the ones who were seeking attention. I think there was a huge
        element of late adolescent ego in the whole <orgName>SDS</orgName> movement. It was all
        about acting out. And, you know, most <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> students—if they were
        going to act out, wanted to act out on the—on the playing field rather than in the newsreel.
        So there was that element in campus. It was very exciting. It was very interesting. And it
        had to do a lot with pulling <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>
        students into the world that they had largely left when they went out to this, you know,
        this ivory tower in the middle of the woods. So it was a very interesting period of time,
        but I never felt alienated from my peers.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. And how about—what about the reaction from the administration, from the
        professors, from the town of <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, besides the other people here
        besides the students?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I think—you know, the amount of inter- —interaction with the people of
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName> was pretty limited. I think they probably felt—my sense was
        that they weren’t particularly—they also looked at the—at—at the theater that went on, the
        circuses, the street theater that went on in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> as something
        that had come in from “away.”[Another voice, and squeaking and other noises.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Do I still have you, <persName>David</persName>?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah, I’m sorry, someone just opened the door.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">No problem. The outside world intruding.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">In—in terms of faculty, I think, you know,—faculty, you know,—as someone who
        had a brief romance with the academic world and was a part of it in other—in other roles
        over the rest of my life, you know, faculty tends to be, you know, two things: much more
        liberal in its—in its viewpoint of things and not necessarily <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>,
        right? In most—most of the faculty, you know, aren’t <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> people, and there is a
        certain—certainly, there was much more I think excitement, much more thrill within the
        faculty, probably, about these student demonstrations than within the student body because,
        you know, a traditionally—and certainly the case today in—in—in academic world,
        in academia, and at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—you know, 85, 90 percent of
        the faculty are of liberal or left-wing persuasion. Those are the kind of people who end up
        in the academic world. And there was much more sympathy and I think a sort of a sense of,
        you know, envy, right? Well, gee, they did this at <placeName>Harvard</placeName>. Why can’t
        they do this at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>? You know, there was a little bit of that going
        on as well. So I think there was probably much more sympathy within the faculty for the
        antiwar movement than perhaps in the student body, itself.I think the administration at this
        point was still reasonably conservative. <persName>John Sloane Dickey</persName> was still
        the president of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and I think there was still elements, older
        elements in the faculty that had been in <name type="event">the Second World War</name>,
        right?—that had—had gone through this experience, themselves. There were people in there who
        had been in the <orgName>military</orgName> rather than people who had sort of spent their entire life, you
        know, in the cocoon of academia.But, you know, again, as an undergraduate living in a house
        or, you know, living in <placeName>Fayerweather</placeName> and going to classes and playing
        sports, you know, it was there. It was around us. You know, it was part of the excitement of
        what was going on. Just as part of the excitement that was going on was the fact that your
        girlfriend was coming up from <placeName>Mount Holyoke</placeName>, that you could sleep
        over in your dorm room, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And maybe you’d go out to the <placeName>Bema</placeName> and smoke dope,
        right? There was a lot of things happening in this period of time, right? I would say that
        the majority of the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> population is getting stoned for the
        first time between <date when="1967">1967</date> and <date when="1969">1969</date>. So you have lots of different things going
        on. It’s not just, you know, drinking Keystone in the fraternity
        basement. It’s going out to the golf course and smoking a joint.So lots of—and listening to
          the Rolling Stones or to Loving [sic; The
          Lovin’] Spoonful. There’s a huge sea change going on in society
        that reaches <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, and part of that sea change had to do with this
        war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and a certain element of seriousness that comes into
        your life when your peers are getting yanked out of their world and sent to someplace where
        they’re getting shot at.And that’s—that’s a chilling experience that certainly was not
        something that—we’d all read about it. It’s something our parents had gone through, but it
        was always with the aura of the triumphalism of <name type="event">the Second World
          War</name>, and now suddenly there’s a war going on we’re not necessarily winning, where
        people your age are dying in obscure rice paddies, being shot by people who were, you know,
        of a different color, were a different race and using, you know, weaponry that comes
        from—from <placeName>China</placeName> and <placeName>Russia</placeName>.So it’s a
        very—very—it was a very exciting and interesting and intense period of time, where
          <placeName>Hanover</placeName> is trying to integrate itself into the world and the
        expectations of the folks who came out of the ’60s like I did, the early ’60s,
        go through this incredible period of change. I would say that between <date when="1965">1965</date> and
          <date when="1969">1969</date>, the four years I spent at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, there
        was probably more social change in this country than there had been in the prior 50
          years. It all happened in this very small period of time, and things were happening
        in parallel, you know, currents.Again, I would go back to the popular culture. I don’t think
        we can underestimate or overestimate—I mean, you can overestimate the power of rock ’n’ roll
        as a way of expressing social change and differences in social attitudes, and it ties into
        the ways people—into the way people related to one another, and then suddenly it does throw
        into stark contrast this now, you know, sort of almost quaint notion of the citizen soldier
        and duty and obedience to authority. That all becomes very questioned.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.So, I mean, in the midst of all of this, you move towards graduation and
        you eventually graduate. What were your thoughts, and did you—you didn’t go immediately into
        serving, is that correct? You had a time afterwards, or—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I—I—I—actually, the way they worked it is that you were commissioned the
          day before you graduated so that you couldn’t graduate until you got your
        commission and was in the service, so I was immediately in the service. I had tried to get a
        postponement of my active duty so I could go to graduate school. I had been accepted at a
        bunch of graduate schools. And that was turned down. So I was in.And, you know, fortunately,
        at least initially, I was in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, and I was assigned to a – great
        term here - a destroyer—how’s that for an aggressive world to live in?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I was a junior officer on a destroyer, and I went off to—to
          <placeName>Boston</placeName>, where my ship was in the yards, and then I was
        home-quartered in <placeName>Newport [Rhode Island]</placeName>, so I
        was in. My friends were—you know, all my peers were doing their best to do something else.
        My best friend was, you know, teaching in college—I mean teaching in high school to get a
        deferment. Two of my other friends went and got psych deferments while these, you know,
        other groups of—other friends of mine were coming from the war at this point because they
        had served their two years as draftees. So I’m in. And I’ve got—you know, and
        I’ve got—you know, and I’m not particularly happy about it [chuckles] because when I—you
        know, when I’m in <placeName>Boston</placeName> and I walk into <placeName>Harvard Square</placeName>, I’m the only
        guy with a crew cut. And God forbid you walk into <placeName>Harvard Square</placeName> in uniform, as I once did,
        and you have people, you know, scream at you, the only place where I was spat on in public
        because I was walking around as a naval officer. Not fun.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. Well, what were your—so what were thoughts on going to
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in general, especially because—I—I don’t know all about the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName>, but serving on a ship, you knew you were going to be on a ship
        and you weren’t going to be fighting on the ground, but over all, what were your thoughts— </u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, let me first of all—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—and concerns?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Let me correct your assumption. I was actually stationed in a Vietnamese
        fishing village, on the ground,—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. </u>
      <u who="COOKE">—as an adviser to the Vietnamese junk force, so I was in a—I was in a fishing
        village north of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, in country. I wasn’t sitting in a
        destroyer.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. </u>
      <u who="COOKE">So I was in—right? And I was, you know, in country, carrying a rifle. [Laughs.]
        So not what I had anticipated! And just as a thumbnail, the reason I got my orders to
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was because I shot my mouth off in the wardrobe—in the ward
        room on my destroyer, basically saying what a stupid war <name type="event">Vietnam</name>
        looked like, and I was told that I wouldn’t really understand it until I’d been there. And
          two weeks later, I had order—orders in country to be a political warfare
        officer in the <orgName>3rd Riverine</orgName>, in <placeName>the Mekong Delta</placeName>, on PBR [Patrol
        Boats, River], which are basically <placeName>Boston</placeName>
        whalers with, you know, a 50 mm machine gun in the bow. [Chuckles.]So I—I got orders into a
        terrible situation. So I had—and—and fortunately, the way things worked out, by the time I
        got there, someone much more serious about their naval career, who wanted to have combat
        experience, took my billet and I ended up doing something a little bit less dangerous.But I
        was—you know, I was in country. I wasn’t, you know, cruising off the coast in the gun line.
        I was scared shitless. I got my orders. I thought—first I—this was—I was—at that point, I
        was on board ship, and we were in the—in the <placeName>Mediterranean
          [Sea]</placeName>, hunting Russian submarines, doing top secret work in the
          Med. And I shot my mouth off, and I then got these orders. My
        executive officer screwed me because he was a <name type="event">Vietnam</name> veteran and
        didn’t like me because I went to <orgName>the Ivy League</orgName>.I got my orders. I was
        terrified, especially when I saw where I was being sent. I—I—I then had a set of decisions,
        you know. Well, what do I do? Do I go to <placeName>Sweden</placeName>? Do I try to get my
        orders changed? What do you do? And in the end, I went—you know, not—you know, not with a
        great deal of enthusiasm but with a sense, you know, in the end that I had made this
        commitment and that’s what you do, you know? You—I had joined the service. I had—I had taken
        my oath, and, you know, I went.You know, terrified my parents, right? And now, as a parent,
        I can—I can only begin to imagine what it would have been like for them, you know, to see me
        off at the airport. [Chuckles.] You know, it was—it was, you know,—it was one of the two or
        three low points in my life when I got those orders, because I’d already had friends killed
        there.And this is now <date when="1971">1971</date>, right? And it’s clear that we’re not going to win
        the war. So this is post-<name type="event">Tet</name>. So I was—you know, I was not a—I was not gung-ho about this.
        And I didn’t volunteer, but I went.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. So what—so can you talk—I—I assume it’s not too classified to talk
        about what you were doing in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Can you explain a bit of what
        your role was and what your job was while you were there?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">All right, well, some of it’s still classified, but not much. What my role was
        eventually, after I—I—when I got to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> on <date when="1971-12-23">December
          23rd</date>, two days before Christmas, I found out that my
        orders to <placeName>the Mekong Delta</placeName> had been taken by someone who was senior
        to me, who wanted the combat experience. And I then sat for a couple of days,
        waiting for an alternate set of orders and finally got a set of orders to be a—a—a watch
        officer with the <orgName>Naval Advisory Group 143</orgName> in <placeName>I
          Corps</placeName>, which is the northern quarter of South
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.And I was stationed in a—in a fishing village called <placeName>Quảng
          Trị</placeName>, and I worked with a set of Vietnamese counterparts, Vietnamese naval
        officers. And essentially, we had a string of radar sites on mountaintops at various places
        along the northern coast of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and we had a group of armored
        junks and patrol craft that were patrolling the coastline to prevent the infiltration of
          <orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName> into <placeName>I Corps</placeName>.And my
        job was to work in the—in the control center in this little fishing village and vector
        armored junks and patrol craft to intercept infiltrators from the northern part of
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, who were coming down the coastline to run arms, you know,
        to the local combatants.And fortunately, most of my job was, you know, sitting in a—sitting
        in a small hooch, you know, working the radios and, you know, acting as a liaison between
        the American advisers who [unintelligible; 1:57:47] the Vietnamese armed forces to
        coordinate both the—the coastal patrol activities and also to coordinate naval gunfire
        support from those destroyers off of the course—off of the coast and the aircraft carriers
        off of the coast of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so that part of what I did was to act as
        an intermediary, to speak to the American advisers that the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
        combat troops, to then pass on information to the gun line so that we could call in naval
        gunfire onto the battlefields where—where—where combat was going on.So I spent a lot of my
        time, you know, forwarding gunfire coordinates to—to bring in fire on—on the enemy. And I
        would stand 12-hour watches, and then I’d get in a <orgName>Jeep</orgName> and go back to
        my—my hooch on, you know, a naval base with—with other naval and—and
          <orgName>Marine</orgName>, you know, soldiers and sailors.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.Could you just clarify one thing for me? What does <placeName>I Corps</placeName> stand
        for?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Okay, the—<placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> during <name type="event">the
          Vietnam War</name> was broken into four military areas, and they were each given a Roman
        numeral designator from north to south, so you have Roman number I, and
        since it looks like an I, it was called <placeName>I Corps</placeName>. And <placeName>I Corps</placeName> was the
        responsibility of <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>. Then you had <placeName>II
          Corps</placeName>, <placeName>III Corps</placeName> and <placeName>IV Corps</placeName>. <placeName>IV
          Corps</placeName> was down in <placeName>the Mekong Delta</placeName>. We basically divided
        the country into four military districts. <placeName>I Corps</placeName> was where all the
        stuff was happening, a lot of the stuff was happening, because that’s the northern part of
          South <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and our northernmost outpost was right on the
          <placeName>DMZ, the [Vietnamese] Demilitarized Zone</placeName> between
          <placeName>North</placeName> and <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>. So during the period that I was there, in
          <date when="1971">’71</date> and <date when="1972">’72</date>, <orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName>
        invaded the South and came through <placeName>I Corps</placeName> and
        got to within about 30 miles of where I was living, so there was a huge battle going on
        during the spring of <date when="1972">1972</date>, called the <name type="event">Easter Offensive</name>, which was kind of the
        dress rehearsal for the eventual fall of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
        hree years later. So the <placeName>I Corps</placeName> was where, you know, the
         <placeName>DMZ</placeName> was, it was where <placeName>Huế</placeName>, the old imperial capital,
        an area in which there was a lot of combat going on and which, by the time I got there,
        there were several North Vietnamese armies that had infiltrated into <placeName>I
          Corps</placeName>. And I used to be able to sit at night at my command post and
        look out over—into the <placeName>A Sầu Valley</placeName> and see—every night there would be—you could see tracer
        fire going back and forth between the—<orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName> and the
        Vietnamese and American forces. So it was like the Fourth of July every night.
        You got to see the firing going on.[unintelligible; 2:01:08]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. I’m sorry?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">No, I was saying there was a lot going on. And we had—you know, we—we—we had,
        you know—give tremendous credit to the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>. We had
        sappers. These are like <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> frogmen [chuckles], which would periodically, you
        know, swim across—there was, like, an inter- —there was, like, a—bay. You know, we were on a
        peninsula. They would swim across the bay and—and—and put [unintelligible; 2:01:39] mines on
        ships and stuff like that. So there was—there was stuff going [on] all the time in that
        particular region in <placeName>I Corps</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Gotcha.And so what—so as an adviser, what kind of advice
        would you be giving to—obviously to help call in naval gunfire, but was there another
        capacity to this?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, it was—it—it—it’s complicated. What in the end you would do is to
        essentially provide a kind of armature around which <orgName>the Vietnamese Navy</orgName>
        would sculpt its—its—its forces. You ended up working with the Vietnamese officers to try to
        get things done. And one of the issues, of course, was the fact that the Vietnamese military
        in the <placeName>South</placeName> wasn’t a terribly motivated or successful operation, so
        that you had a lot of American advisers trying to get their Vietnamese counterparts to
        actually go and engage with the enemy. But, you know, basically you work in parallel, you
        know, and in some ways, you know, it was, you know, the Americans running the war for the
        Vietnamese.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So how did you approach this relationship, then, when it’s clear to you that
        they’re not—they’re not quite a competent force or competent enough force to necessarily
        win, and the overall war is not going your way?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, you do the best you can. And it—it gets you into the—for me, it was—you
        know, I—when I got my orders, I was then for six months of training in
          <placeName>Coronado, California</placeName>, during which—because I
        don’t remember—I learned Vietnamese, I took an extended course in Vietnamese history and
        culture, and I also learned how to shoot a bunch of different weapons, right?—and how to
        run, you know, a patrol boat and learned all kinds of mechanical things.Part of what you
        learned was how complex Vietnamese society is and that there are lots of different elements
        in society in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and a lot of interesting history, right?
        Because <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was part of French Indochina, and the French had been
        there 300 years, right? You know, the French colonized Southeast
          Asia, through the Jesuits, in the 1640s, about the same time that
        the Pilgrims were coming to <placeName>the United States</placeName>. So
        there’s been a longstanding French presence there.Since I’m working in the
          <orgName>Navy</orgName>, I tend to be working—my Vietnamese counterparts tend to be
        Vietnamese who had become part of the French colonial society, so most of my
        contemporary—most of—most of my advisees are French speakers as well as Vietnamese speakers,
        so I’m speaking to them in French more than in—in—in Vietnamese because my Vietnamese is
        terrible. I’m sort of tone deaf, and Vietnamese is an intonated language, like Chinese, so
        it’s kind of hard to understand unless you have a very good ear.And I’m—I’m trying to—to
        work with them, to motivate them to do things. A lot of them are in the navy because their
        parents are well enough wired into Vietnamese society so they’re not in the army, where
        there’s a tremendous, you know, casualty rate. The navy—you know, it is a safer way to go at
        things, right? So you’re tending to—the people I tended to deal with, the officers I was
        dealing with that were in <orgName>the Vietnamese Navy</orgName> tended to come from the
        colonial society, and the enlisted men I’m dealing with in the Vietnamese Navy tend to
        come—tend to be fishermen, because, you know, they’re people who know boats.And one of the
        things you discover in the mix of Vietnamese society, which is a bunch of different cultures
        together, is that there is a core group of Vietnamese who are Catholic, who have been
        essentially, you know, integrated into western society. They’re sort of the colonial
        lackeys. And you have a lot of fishermen, who are violently anti-communist. And one of the
        things—one of the tragedies for me is a lot of the <orgName>Vietnamese Navy</orgName> guys I
        worked with had tattoos all over them that said “Death to the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>.” Can you imagine
        what happened to them after we left?I mean, there’s lots of stories here. I mean, the
        biggest tragedy was what happened to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> after we left, because
        certainly, all the people that had been coopted by us, all ended up, you know, going into
        concentration camps if they weren’t killed outright. There’s a huge disaster at the end of
        all this that we kind of walk away from and forget about, and, you know, for those of us who
        were advisers and who worked day to day with the Vietnamese, we know that each of the people
        that we worked with who didn’t manage to get out of there in <date when="1975">1975</date> ended up
        either being killed or sent to a concentration camp.So there’s a—there’s a huge—I mean,
        there’s a lot of problems, and 35,000—or was it 53,000 Americans die
        and are wounded in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. There are hundreds of thousands of
        Vietnamese who we supported, who end up going into terrible situations after we leave. And
        no one talks about that, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, you know, the biggest crime we perpetrated there, in some ways, was
        the betrayal of the people that we were ostensibly, you know, supporting, because we cut and
        ran. You know, not that you were going to win. I mean, it’s a very complicated—I have very
        complicated feelings about it. You know, for me, the—the best symbol of why we lost, is
        that, you know, I was in a fishing village, and it was on a peninsula, and then there was a
        big sort of internal harbor area. If you look at the map of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, in
          <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>, where international shipping would come in. And
        ammunition ships would come in to <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> harbor and anchor out in this
        internal harbor, and they would unload their munitions onto barges. So you would have these
        barges that are sort of floating off of the coast where we—where our fishing village is, and
        there’s, like, 50[,000], 60,000 tons of ammunition on this barge, and it’s being protected
        by <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName>. So they’re army guys sitting on this barge,
        protecting it from the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> frogmen who come in every week and try
        to blow it up. And—and the group I work with run little patrol boats around and—and visit
        the barges at night to make sure everything’s all right. Night in and night out, you’d go
        out to one of these barges, 50[,000], 60,000 tons of—of munitions on the barge, and every
        one of the Vietnamese soldiers would be asleep. Okay?Put that in context. This is what
        you’re dealing with, right? You’re dealing with a situation in which these guys are sitting
        on 40,000 dol- —40,000 tons of TNT. They know that there are <orgName>North
        Vietnamese</orgName> frogmen in the water coming in, and they’re—they go to sleep, right? That’s when
        I knew that we were never going to win the war [chuckles], right? Because how do deal with
        that kind of mentality?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So, you know, it was—you know, it was—it was not a happy, you know, situation,
        and yet, you know, the Vietnamese I worked with—charming people. Educated. When I first came
        into my little hooch, my Vietnamese counterpart was reading <persName>Proust</persName>, in
        French, of course.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Complicated.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So—so how do you—how would you find the motivation to be doing your job when
        it seems like a lot of the situation was just beyond your control or hopeless, in some
        sense?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I guess it’s like being a <orgName>Republican</orgName> when <persName>[Donald J.]
          Trump</persName> is nominated for president. [Chuckles.] I don’t know.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, <orgName>it’s</orgName>—there was a certain element of
        self-preservation, and there was certainly an ele- —a certain element of professionalism,
        right? You were expected to—you know, I was an American naval officer. I had been a
        fleet-qualified officer of the deck. I had done—you know, I knew how to drive a ship. I—I
        knew how to, you know, shoot a gun. I knew how to do the technology. I just did my job as
        best as I could—you know, just as I do the best job I can now, years later, as a lawyer. You
        know, maybe you have a client you don’t love. You still, you know, try to do the best job
        you can.And, you know, it was also enlightened self-interest at a certain point, right?
        Because, you know, if you couldn’t motivate these guys to go out and—and stand guard duty,
        someone was going to come in and shoot you [chuckles], so you—you tried to do the best you
        could in a- —you know, in a com- —originally for self-preservation and—and in terms of
        your—of a sense of professionalism. You know, again, you’re still—you know, go back to this
        Old World—you know, pre- —pre-1960s image of—of service and leadership. You’re still—you’re
        still in the uniform. You’re a naval officer. You have a sense of history, a sense of duty,
        a sense of obligation, and you do the best you can in this situation.And I think that’s
        probably true of anyone who’s involved in—in a wartime situation. You know,
        it’s—it’s confusing. It’s—it’s tragic. It’s—it’s appalling. It’s, you
        know, surreal. You know, stuff that went on there, you know,—the four years I spent in the
        service, I did things and I saw things that I would never have been able to imagine in the
        rest of my life, you know? You know, there’s dead bodies all over the place. You know,
        people are shooting at you. You know, it’s just that—but that’s the world you’re in, and
        you—you—you do your best to do—to—to play your role and—and to survive. In the end it’s sort
        of primal.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. If you—if you are comfortable with it, could you walk me through or
        mention a few of those moments you just referred to?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">[Sighs.] Well, you know, we—we certainly had instances in which we were getting
        shelled, and it was—it was, you know, bizarre in the sense that, you know, you’d be in your
        hooch and there was a <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> sapper unit across the bay from us, and they
        would—every night, they would shoot rockets across the—the bay, and the rockets would land
        in and around our compound, so that, you know, you had no idea when they were coming. They
        would just sort of land randomly. And on one occasion, I had one go over my head fairly
        close to me and land across the street and kill a couple of people. That was probably the
        closest I got to, you know, real danger. And then for days after that, I had a
        hard time sleeping, right? Because who knows what was going to come through the roof?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, you know, there was just—people were dying all over the place. I was
        sitting in my—my hooch or sitting in, you know, at—at—at my command post, and I heard this
        tremendous explosion, and debris rained down the area. There—there was an American jet that
        had collided with a Vietnamese spotter plane right over where we were, and debris rained
        down—it was a huge explosion, right? And debris rains down on our little command post,
        including pieces of the pilot, right?How do you deal with that, you know? You—we ended up
        having someone’s foot in the refrigerator. You know, it’s surreal. You know, that’s
        just—that’s something you don’t, you know, come in contact with in the rest of the
        world.And—and—and how surreal was it? Driving—you know, driving from where I lived out to
        where I—where our command post was, you would drive down this road, and at a certain point
        when I was there, the—the <orgName>Seabees</orgName> came in, and they dug out a huge trench next to the road,
        about 15, 20 feet deep, and then as you drove by the next day, that—they then
        build this huge trench with <persName>Jeeps</persName> and trucks and military equipment,
        and they buried it because they—because at this point there were Vietnamese—the
        Vietnamization had happened. We were pulling people out, and they just
        buried tens of thousands of dollars’ worth of equipment. Just buried it, right? So
        here’s—here’s, you know, millions of d- —you know, huge amounts of money just being
        buried.We had a—we had a—a—a radar station on the top of a—of a hill nearby, called
          <placeName>Monkey Mountain</placeName>, and I would drive up to see the sailors running
        the radar station. On the way up, at a certain point about three-quarters of the way up,
        there was the tail end of an American [McDonald Douglas] F-4 [Phantom II]
        fighter plane—I don’t know if you’ve ever heard the expression of “auguring in”—that had
        augured into the mountainside. So you drive past—you’d be going up this road, there would be
        the tail section of an American jet buried in the side of the—of the mountain, you know,
        with graffiti on it [chuckles], right? And, of course, there was some guy in that jet, who
        took it in, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So there’s—you’re—you’re surrounded by this chaotic world. You would—I would
        drive to work, and alongside the road there would be troops of monkeys. You know, you’re in
        a tropical environment. One day, you know, driving back from my 12-hour shift
        at this control boat, there was an anaconda that had come across the road that had stolen a
        pig from the local village. And it was, like, you know, a 30-foot snake—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Wow.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—slithering across the road, and you drove—I drove over it in the
          <orgName>Jeep</orgName>, and it didn’t even flinch, right? So you’re in this world where
        there—there are giant, you know, anacondas and boa constrictors and monkeys, and, you know,
        you’re—you’re just in a very different environment, and it’s bizarre. It’s absolutely
        bizarre, because it’s a beautiful place. The area we were in—in—in—outside of <placeName>Da
          Nang</placeName>, prior to the war, had been a French resort area, okay. And I had the
        experience, on a couple of occasions, when I had an afternoon off, of getting together with
        a couple of my buddies, taking a short <orgName>Jeep</orgName> ride over to the coastline,
        and we went surfing! Okay? <placeName>China Beach</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">There was a TV show called <placeName>China Beach</placeName>. That was near
        where I was stationed. We went—I went surfing there. It was a good break, okay?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Guys would go waterskiing behind their PBRs.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, it was just—it was—it was a—it was a surreal environment, in which
        you were, you know,—it was just very different than anything that—that—that you would
        experience. And in the midst of this, we were—you know, we were in—outside of <placeName>Da
          Nang</placeName>. At this point in the history of the war, after the <name type="event">Tet</name>, the war ceased to
        become a guerilla war between the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName> and the <orgName>South
        Vietnamese government</orgName> because it had—What happened in the <name type="event">Tet</name>, even though it was a huge
        political victory for the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>—basically, after
          <name type="event">Tet</name>, the—the uprising failed, but all of the—the infrastructure of
          the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName> came to the surface, because they thought they
        were going to take the country over. So in the—in the months following <name type="event">Tet</name>,
        the—the <orgName>CIA</orgName> and <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName> managed to
        liquidate the entire <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>, so by the end of the war, there is no
        indigenous communist revolution in most of South—<placeName>South
          Vietnam</placeName>. The war becomes a—a—a classic war between <orgName>the North
          Vietnamese Army</orgName> and <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName>, and it’s a
        situation in which <orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName> is better armed and just
        a—a—a—a better military organization. And once the Americans pull out their support, the
          <placeName>South</placeName> falls. That’s the basic story in a nutshell.So where I was
        living, you know, in—in and around a Vietnamese fishing village, no one was trying to—you
        know, the people who were trying to kill me were the—were the—were <orgName>the North
          Vietnamese Army</orgName> across the bay, right? And when we went out to our—I went
        to—some of our—we had a—we had a radar station on top of a place called
          <placeName>Bastogne</placeName> [pronounced bass-TONE], which was a fire base in
          <placeName>the A Sầu Valley</placeName>, if you ever studied Vietnamese military
        history.And I—we would fly out there in helicopters, and I would work, you know, with the
        local radar guys. I remember sitting in the fire base with a pair of binoculars, watching
        North Vietnamese trucks running ammunition along—you know, near the Laotian border. So the
        war changed over the time I was there from the guerilla war into a much more formal type of
        warfare situation.Most of the population I lived with—they weren’t—you know, it wasn’t like
        these poor slobs in—in <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> and <placeName>Iraq</placeName>,
        where everybody’s trying to kill you all the time, right? Most of the population in
          <persName>Da Nang</persName>—they didn’t want the communists to be in the country, and
        they weren’t particularly trying to kill you, They weren’t particularly happy about your
        being there, but I never felt, you know, the notion that—it was hardly likely that an
        IUD [improvised explosive device] was going to hit me as I was driving
        in my <orgName>Jeep</orgName>, you know, although I did have a couple of instances in which
        I went to a local barbershop and I had a Vietnamese lady barber, you know, cut my hair and
        then, you know, give me a shave with a straight razor, right? So you’re sitting in the
        chair, and she lathers up and picks up the straight razor, and she’s Vietnamese, right. And
        she’s kind of shaving your—your neck.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And [unintelligible; 2:21:33], Do I really want to be here? Why am I doing
        this? [Laughs.] You know. I doubt you’d do that right now in
        <placeName>Iraq</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So, [unintelligible; 2:21:43]—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So what was—I’m sorry? Yeah. So you briefly touched on it just now, but I want
        to maybe hear further. Did you have a strong interaction with the local Vietnamese
        community? You were in a fishing village.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, yes and no. At the time that we were there, <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>
        was a closed city, so—that was the major city south of where we were stationed. And the
        American military weren’t allowed in—in <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, right? That was a
        closed city. I interacted—I could go in because I was an adviser. I had a special adviser ID
        card. Most of my interactions were with my—the people that I was advising. And that was on a
        day-to-day basis. They were young, you know, Vietnamese mil- —you know, naval officers, and
        basically we would—we would work together, and you develop, you know, some kind of a—some
        degree of—of working friendship. You know, some of them weren’t particularly interested
        in—in dealing with you or necessarily sharing much of their lives. Others were more
        friendly.So I did not develop, you know, any—any lasting friendships, mostly I think because
        of the language difficulty and the fact that at this point, you know, I was very
        self-protective. I was not particularly adventuresome. I rarely went out, you know, to
        mingle with—with my counterparts. Once or twice I would go—go over and have dinner, but I—I
        didn’t—I wasn’t aggressively engaged in trying to integrate with the local society, in part
        just out of fear, to be candid.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. And so you—you briefly mentioned the <name type="event">Easter invasion</name>. Can you go a
        little more into the action you saw during that? Because it sounds like they got very close
        to your location.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, they did, they did. And to put it in- —to describe it briefly, in
        probably pril of 19- —<date when="1972-04">April</date> and <date when="1972-05">May of 1972</date>,
         the <orgName>North Vietnamese Army</orgName> ran—you know, invaded the
          <placeName>South</placeName>. They came around <placeName>the Demilitarized
          Zone</placeName> that separated <placeName>North</placeName> and
        <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, with about 50[,000] to 75,000 troops. One of our naval
        bases, where we had advisers, was right at the border, in a town called <placeName>Cửa
          Việt</placeName>. And I had the experience of, you know, being on duty when the <orgName>North
        Vietnamese</orgName> started shelling <placeName>Cửa Việt</placeName>. And it readily became apparent
        that there was a major invasion going on, and to make a long story short—at this point, we
        had—we were in the middle of Viet- —so-called Vietnamization,
        right?—which was something that came in with <persName>[President Richard M.]
        Nixon</persName>’s <name type="event">election in ’68</name>, because he had a “secret,” you
        know, plan for ending the war, which basically was gradually turning it back over to the
        Vietnamese, which was just, you know, a euphemism for getting out, but getting out
        gradually.So we were suddenly in a situation in which we had a lot of advisers in <placeName>I Corps</placeName> in
        the North, and we were relying upon <orgName>the Vietnamese army</orgName> to protect us from the
          North Vietnamese, and some of the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> roll across the border, led
        by a—led by tanks. And <placeName>Cửa Việt</placeName> falls within 48 hours.We end up sending
        boats north from where I was to evacuate the American advisers and as much of the local
        population as we could, so we—we sent a bunch of—of LSTs. It was Landing
          Ship, Tank. They were sort of, you know, amphibious vessels that we had given
        to the Vietnamese and were still operating. So we’re trying to evacuate folks—our—our—our
        folks up north as the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> fight their way south. And it’s sort of like a—a—a—a
        hot knife through butter. Within the space of a week, they have recaptured
          <placeName>Huế</placeName>, which is the imperial—the former imperial capital of
         South—of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, where a lot of intensive
        fighting had occurred during <name type="event">Tet</name>.And at—at this point, you know,
        we’re—we’re pulling troops out, right? We have our—we’re pulling advisers out of some of our
        more northerly radar stations and watching, you know, the strategic situation about how far
        these guys are going to—whether the whole country is going to fall, because, you know, after
        the fall of <placeName>Huế</placeName>, the next major Vietnamese city is <placeName>Da
          Nang</placeName>, and we’re north of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>.So there’s a period of time in which we are
        essentially getting ready to pull out, right? The Americans were figuring,
          Jeez, we’re gonna have <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>—we’re gonna have <orgName>North
        Vietnamese</orgName> tanks rolling down the street here in a couple of days. So there are
        preliminary orders—preliminary orders go out, you know, to get ready to—to pack your bags,
        essentially.At the same time, the <orgName>American [sic; U.S.] 7th
          Fleet</orgName>, which is still around, is massing of the—the coast of <placeName>I
          Corps</placeName>, and one of the things that I’m doing at this point is
        working with the American advisers to call artillery fire onto the advancing <orgName>North
        Vietnamese</orgName> troops coming down the—the coast, along the coastal area. They’d taken
         <placeName>Cửa Việt</placeName>. They’d taken <placeName>Huế</placeName>. But suddenly, you know, you’ve got a
        couple—another aircraft carrier or two comes over, and suddenly the entire gun line is—you
        know, the entire <orgName>7th Fleet</orgName> is now off of the coast of <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>,
        you know, pouring artillery fire onto the advancing <orgName>North Vietnamese
        Army</orgName>. And we’re trying to coordinate with them to have that—that fire be
        effective.And at the same time, we’re trying to get, you know, our advisers out of there. At
        this point, we’ve already pulled our advisers out of <placeName>Cửa Việt</placeName>. We pull
        our advisers out of the <placeName>Bastogne</placeName> place, where I had been a couple
          of weeks earlier and sort of looked through the binoculars and seen the trucks
        running, the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> trucks, right? So that falls.There is a huge movement of
        population down the major highway, down probably [National] Route 3, coming—all the—all the
        Vietnamese are fleeing south to avoid the—the communist—you know, the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>
        troops, so there’s this huge chaos. The Vietnamese—<orgName>the South Vietnamese
          Army</orgName> has largely collapsed. They’re all in retreat. And it’s kind of touch and
        go [laughs], right?And then I had this incredible experience of one evening a bunch of young
        <orgName>American [U.S.] Marine Corps</orgName> officers suddenly
        arrive at our barracks where we were living, and they—they’d been sent up—they’d been—you
        know, by their superiors, to go in and to—and to man—they’re going to assume leadership of
        the remains of <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName>, in particular the remains of
        the South Vietnamese armor, the tanks.So I’ll never forget sitting around the hooch one
        evening with these young second and first lieutenant <orgName>Marines</orgName>. The next day,
        they’re going north, and they’re going to take over these tanks and try to stop
          the—<orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName>, right? And I’m thinking, Jesus
          Christ! You know, these guys—they—they know they’re going into this totally
        chaotic situation—and these are my contemporaries right there, and we’re all—you know,
        we’re—we’re 23, we’re 24 years old, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">And you have to, again, put this in perspective. These are all guys—all these
        guys involved here are your age, right?—or pretty close, right? So you’re kids, right? If
        you think you’re grown up, you’re a kid, right? You’re not fully mature until your
          24, right? None of them were 24. So these guys then go up and get into
        Vietnamese tanks and, through their—their simple bravery and the support from <orgName>the
          7th Fleet</orgName>, they manage to stop the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>. And
        the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> essentially get trapped along the—the coastline, and for the next
          several weeks, the—an entire <orgName>North Vietnamese Army</orgName> is decimated,
        and they take tremendous casualties.And that’s the end of the <name type="event">Easter
          Invasion</name> in <date when="1972">1972</date>. And the reason that the <name type="event">Eastern
          Invasion</name> failed is because the Americans still provided air support and naval
        gunfire support, and there were still advisers who were able to go in and provide some spine
        to the—<orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName>.What happens wo years
          later: Same scenario, but at that point, you have [the]
          <name type="event">Watergate [scandal]</name>, you have a change in administration, you know,
          <persName>Gerald [R.] Ford [Jr.]</persName> is the president, and the Americans decide
        they’re not going to support the Vietnamese, and <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> falls.I was
        there sort of for the dress rehearsal of this, and what it—what it proved is (a) that <orgName>North
        Vietnamese</orgName> were willing to lose tens of thousands of troops to achieve their military goals,
        that we never really created a—a sufficiently and uniformly well-organized <orgName>South
          Vietnamese Army</orgName> to be able to resist them, and that as soon as the Americans
        cease to provide support, that the whole situation would collapse.And, you know, it—it
        provides essentially a pattern for so many other American involvements in other kinds of
        foreign wars where you’re trying to defend a colonial empire of the French or the British,
        and it’s exactly what’s going on, you know, in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>, right? As long
        as the Americans are there, dying, you can hold the country together. You pull the Americans
        out, it falls apart.So it—it provides, I think, a—a lens into a lot of the problems of
        American foreign policy in terms of nation building or nation support, and it makes them
        very cynical about the opportunity to—to succeed in that with that kind of a strategy, and
        it also makes you tremendously sympathetic for the poor slobs that, you know, rely on the
        Americans to protect them when the Americans pull out.I mean, that’s sort of—you know, what
        did I see of the war? I saw the dress rehearsal for the end, you know, and I had a couple of
        instances in which, you know, I got shot at. I never had to, you know, advance under fire. I
        was certainly not, you know, you know, a grunt, you know, who was, you know—who—I think
        that’s incredible courage, to do that. I was—I was an adviser [chuckles], right? I was a
        staff adviser, you know.But I—you know, I—I saw a lot of stuff, and I was involved, you
        know, sort of at one remove in—in—in combat, and, you know, it was dangerous, but it wasn’t
        at all like the situation that, you know, my contemporaries had who were, you know, humping
        in the—in—in—in—in the—in the rice paddies. That was another world entirely that I
        fortunately avoided.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. Did you realize at the time that you were witnessing kind of this dress
        rehearsal for the end, as you put it? Or was that something that kind of came to you
        afterwards?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I would say a lot of this is retrospect. I mean, you know, you didn’t
        know about <date when="1975">1975</date> in
        <date when="1972">1972</date>. But it—it did impress on me the fragility of the military situation and
        the essential role that, you know, <placeName>the United States</placeName> was playing
        in—in supporting the entire South Vietnamese, you know, social structure. You know, we
        were—we were propping them up. There was no doubt about that. And it was also clear that,
        while, you know, <orgName>the Vietnamese Navy</orgName> wasn’t a bad organization. You know,
        there were some competent officers that I worked with that—you know, <orgName>the Vietnamese
          Army</orgName> was just so spotty in terms of quality. And there was also, you know, a
        huge difference between the—the mindset of the <placeName>North</placeName> and the
          <placeName>South</placeName>.You know, you were in a situation—it sort of gets you back
        to, you know, other examples of 20th-century history. You were fighting a
        totalitarian government in which there was, you know, total dominance by the <orgName>
          Communist Party</orgName> and a kind of pervasive indoctrination so that these guys were
        willing to lay down their lives by the tens of thousands, or were compelled to do that.And
        in the <placeName>South</placeName> you had a very different world. It was a much more, you
        know, cosmopolitan world. It was a world in which there wasn’t that kind of a—a—a central
        ideology. It was a much more corrupt political system, in some ways. So, you know, it
        provided a lesson about, you know, the—the power of, you know, totalitarian governments
        to—to muster and to, you know, motivate people to go out and die for a certain kind of
        political idea, you know.And it’s not unlike, you know, dealing with <orgName>ISIS
        [Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, officially
        known as Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant, or ISIL]</orgName>. You know,
        you have—you have true believers. I mean, I think of these guys who used to, you know, swim
        across the bay with explosives tied to themselves and then try to blow up these ships. I
        mean, incredible courage. Willingness to die. You know, in the end, it tells you a lot about
        the nature of motivation of an army. There are lots of analogies to that.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So it was very interesting. And I think it reflects a lot of—you know, it makes
        one very cynical. It makes one very cynical about American foreign military involvement, you
        know, how—you know, what—what—what’s the end game? That was the thing in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, is we never had an end game. And it’s not unlike
        what—what—what—what’s occurred in the past, in your lifetime in the Middle
          East.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. So how much longer were you in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> after
        this? When did you finish, I’ll ask, then?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I—I was not there much longer. I was there until June. And
        then—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay, so only a couple of months.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yeah. So I was, you know—I—and what happened was that, you know, during
          this period of <date when="1971">1971</date> to <date when="1972">’72</date>—and, again, this is interesting in terms of
        context—there—there’s a—there’s a presidential election going on, right? And
          <persName>Nixon</persName> is up for reelection. And one of the motivating factors in the
        reelection is getting <name type="event">Vietnam</name> dealt with. So you have <persName>[Secretary of
          State] Henry [A.] Kissinger</persName> negotiating with the
        Vietnamese in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, North Vietnamese in
        <placeName>Paris</placeName>. And you have the fulfillment of the so-called Vietnamization
        program, in which, in order to address political pressures back in the
          <placeName>States</placeName>, <persName>Nixon</persName> decides that he’s going to pull
        the vast majority of Americans out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and leave the war to
        the Vietnamese.So one of the things that happens, you know, between May and
          June is that the—the president announces that we now have—there’s now an
        all-volunteer American f- —that we’re withdrawing our troops, no more—because the whole
        issue was, like, putting draftees into foreign wars, which we could—you know, which is
        another topic of discussion entirely. But there’s an announcement by <orgName>the White
          House</orgName> that there are no longer any draftees in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>;
        it’s an all-volunteer force. And I’m there, and I’m not a volunteer [laughs], right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So I end up—my mother ends up calling my congressman [laughs] and pointing out
        that her son is there and he’s not a volunteer, and within a couple of weeks, I
        get called back to the—I get orders out. And, you know, basically my unit is—is largely
        withdrawn at that point as part of the withdrawal. Some of my—some of the guys I was there
        with remained—remained for another couple of months, but by—you know, within
          three or four months after that, the American military presence is gone from
          three quarters of a million to, you know, fifty or sixty thousand. So
        there’s, like, a huge period of American withdrawal after the—the <name type="event">Easter
          Invasion</name> is stopped, right? And then there’s a period of time in which another
        generation of North Vietnamese soldiers have to be trained, right? Because they just lost
        fifty, sixty thousand troops. They’ve had—they’ve—they’ve been—they’ve had a huge—their
        entire armies [unintelligible; 2:41:00] all got decimated. None of them made it back. So
        there’s a period of [unintelligible; 2:41:05].And then—and then you have the—the next—the
        next wave of it happen several years later, and then the whole thing just falls
        apart. And by next—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So I’m—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So by <date>1975</date>, there are a couple of thousand Americans left in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. I’m sure that when you were leaving <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>,
        relief was near the top of your mind, but what else were you feeling when you finally got to
        go home or at least back to the—the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I mean, it was—it was elation, right? You know, I got out with my—you
        know, in one piece. I was—I was extremely happy. I also realized that, you know, I was now
          three years into a four-year military commitment. I kind of
        thought they’d let me out, and I applied for an early out. I wasn’t given it.But I
        came—coming out of a—you know, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and out of a combat situation,
        I had the choice of billet, so I ended up electing to do shore duty in
          <placeName>Boston</placeName>, right? And I spent my last year as an
        administrative officer in South <placeName>Boston</placeName>, you know, taking, you know,
        night courses at <placeName>Harvard</placeName>. [Chuckles.] So I was—you know, I was out. And I
        was, you know,—you know, I—I couldn’t have been happier to be out of there.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You know, it was a real—there was some real anxiety. And also my—it drove my
        parents nuts because that was a war that was so thoroughly covered by the—by the media. My
        parents—there was—during this period of time, when all the nasty things were happening
          (April, May, June), my parents were watching <persName>Walter [L.]
        Cronkite [Jr.]</persName>, and there was a report of an American, a small naval radar station that had
        been overrun, right?—by the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>. And my parents thought that was our base that
        had been overrun.So my parents had the experience of calling up <orgName>CBS
        [Evening] News</orgName>—they couldn’t get any answer from the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, of course—to
        try to find out which base exactly it was that had been overrun, to see if I was still alive
        or not, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So that’s the kind of—you know, my—as wonderful as it was for me, it was
        probably more wonderful for my parents when I flew out of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, you
        know, on my way home.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And what was—what was the impact of the war on your family and I guess in your
        relationship with your family while you were away for so long?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I—I think it only strengthened my relationship with my family. I think
        that coming back from that experience, there was a fundamental change in my relationship
        with my dad in the sense that it became sort of a marker that represented my—my full
        maturity in terms of the way he dealt with me. So it was just—I think he treated me much
        more as a—he treated me as an adult after that experience. And he—you know, he wasn’t going
        to second guess me about things, because I had been through that experience. So in some
        ways, it was a watershed experience.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.Was it difficult to readjust to life, coming back?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">In retrospect, I had—I had some difficulties, yes. I was fortunate in the sense
        that I had this period of a year of shore duty, essentially, to depressurize,
        although I ended up, you know, having a near fatal car accident, having a really screwed up
        emotional involvement. [Chuckles.] You know, clearly there were—there were things that were
        still—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—needed to be settled, but I was blessed in the sense that when I got back,
        I—I—I went—I—I—I applied and got into graduate school. And after I finished my fourth
          year in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, I went off to <placeName>[the University of]
          Cambridge</placeName> for two years, and it was like going back to Hogwarts
          [School of Witchcraft and Wizardry]. I mean, I had—I
        had a scarf. I had a bicycle. [Chuckles.] I went to a university that—you know, my college
        was founded in <date when="1352">1352</date>. I lived in this incredible world that I’d always
        fantasized about. And getting back to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—you know, I so loved my
        undergraduate experience at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> that all I wanted to do when I got
        out of the <orgName>military</orgName> was to go back to school, so I had this chance to go and spend two
          years at <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> and read English at
          <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>, which was in some ways like an extension of the time I
        had at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, so I—I had this wonderful opportunity on the <name type="event">G.I. Bill
          [erviceman’s Readjustment Act of 1944]</name> to—to fulfill my
        fantasies in a world that was as far removed from, you know, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
        as you can imagine. So I was very lucky. And the <orgName>Navy</orgName> paid for that.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. And what did you end up—right. And what did you end up studying or
        getting your graduated degree in?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">In English literature. So I—you know, I wrote my the- —master’s these on
          <persName>Joseph Conrad</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Gotcha. And—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yes?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">That’s pretty fitting, I guess, Heart of Darkness.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, it was very fitting.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So two significant event- —yeah. Sorry, I think the—the audio here is messing
        up a bit.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Okay. Well,—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Can you still hear me?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yeah, I can. Can you hear me?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Pause.]</u>
      <u who="COOKE">You may have [cross-talk; unintelligible; 2:47:55].</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah, okay, I can hear you know.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Are you still there?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Pause.] Yeah, no, I’m still here. Can you hear me?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I can hear you.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Pause.] Okay, great. So I—I had two significant events, kind of, after you
        left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I was wondering your thoughts on them. The first is the
        cease fire that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> signs in <date when="1973">1973</date>, and the second
        is—I mean, the final or the fall of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> in
          <date when="1975">1975</date>. If I could just hear your thoughts or reactions to those when they
        occurred.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, interesting, in—in terms of timing because that period of
          <date when="1973">1973</date> to <date when="1975">1975</date>—I’m out of the country. I’m reading English at
          <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>, right?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">So I’m not reading the American newspapers. I’m not watching television. I’m
        kind of divorced from it all. What is my reaction to the—you know, the peace negotiations
        and the—it’s probably a pretty cynical one. You know, having been through what I went
        through in <date when="1972">’72</date>, you know, it becomes pretty clear to me that during this period
        of time, <date when="1973">’73</date>- —you know, let’s mark it by <name type="event">Watergate</name>, right?
        Post-Water- —after Nixon’s—<persName>Nixon</persName> resigns, <persName>Ford</persName>
        becomes president, and at this point, no one in <placeName>America</placeName> wants to deal
        with <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> anymore. So I’m not at all surprised, certainly in
          <date when="1975">’75</date>, when the whole thing falls—I’ve been there, I’ve done that, I’ve seen
        that happen before. I’ve seen the—the—the lines of refugees coming south, right? So there’s
        a certain sense of inevitability, déjà vu. In terms of the peace treaty, you know, I don’t
        think I ever felt that it was anything other than wallpaper, right? You’re papering over the
        situation. You’re trying to have—you know, there was this term, “peace with honor.” Pretty
        cynical about that at the time that the people are talking about it, right?
        We’re—we’re—we’re cutting out. And, you know, probably the right decision in some ways, but
        also the sense of—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—the people—you know, I think about—you know, more than others, perhaps, I
        think about what it means for the people that I worked with day in and day out during the
        time I was there. I think about these guys, you know, who have “Death to the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>”
        tattooed on their arms, right? I think about them a lot.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">What have we done? What have we accomplished? You know? And I think about, you
        know,—I think about <persName>[William S.] “Bill” Smoyer</persName> <orgName>[Class of
          1967]</orgName>, who I was in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> with. I think about <persName>[J. Robert]
        “Robbie” Peacock [II]</persName>, <orgName>Class of 1968]</orgName>, who I played lacrosse with, the guys who
        died there, right? To what end? <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> guys. You know, tragedy.And,
        you know, look at it—and then what’s interesting, to look at it in perspective,
          <date when="1975">1975</date> and on, the Vietnamese fight a war with the Chinese. There’s a border
        war between <placeName>China</placeName> and <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, which you may
        or may not be aware of. And they sustain 100,000 casualties fighting the Chinese.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Right? And—and one of the major rationales for the Americans being in
          <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> was to prevent the domino effect of the Chinese, you
        know, taking over Southeast Asia. So it’s—it is—it is just so ripe
        with tragedy and irony. You know, and a stark contrast to the world that I grew up in.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So moving on from there,—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Sorry? Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I was just going to say, you know, a sharp contrast—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Sorry? In start [sic; stark] contrast—I lost you after—</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Yeah, in sharp contrast to the—to this vision of the—of the post-<name
          type="event">World War II</name> American society that I grew up in, right? We’ve come a
        long way from the world of <date when="1964">1964</date>,—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">—when everybody else in my high school had a crew cut and I went off and joined
        the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. So—so into this new life, this <name type="event">post-Vietnam</name>
        life, can you tell me a little bit about where you went, like, after you finished
          <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> with your graduate degree?</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Sure. No, I—I then ended up integrating myself into society. I—I—I got my
        graduate degree at <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>. I had a wonderful experience there.
        Went on and went to <placeName>Harvard Law School</placeName>, had a somewhat less wonderful
        experience there and became an attorney. And I’ve been practicing law since I graduated from
          <placeName>Harvard</placeName> in <date when="1978">1978</date>. And very lucky. I’m an entertainment
        attorney. I do motion picture and television work, and I’ve been very fortunate, you know,
        because not every job in the legal profession is so wonderful. I was—I just had good
        fortune.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. And I guess the point I want to end on now is
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> obviously had had a strong impact on your life., I was just
        wondering if this so-called specter—like, your <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience
        really still im- —has impacted you over the years since you’ve left, since
        you’ve not physically been in the region.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Well, I—I think the answer is that it has had a continuing effect on my life,
        although it is an effect that has diminished over the passage of time. I used to dream a lot
        about it, and I don’t anymore. I—I think I probably, maybe had one dream about being back in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in the past couple of years. I used to dream
        about it pretty frequently.I think it’s had a lasting impression in terms of my appreciation
        of politics. It—it’s made me—it still leaves a lot of am- —ambivalent feelings about
          <placeName>America</placeName>’s role in the world and American foreign policy. It’s made
        me have a greater appreciation, certainly, for what it means to be in the military and what
        it means to—you know, on an individual level. And I think it’s also given me a deeper
        awareness and sensitivity to world history. It’s made me much more interested in world
        history and understanding how these things happen, especially in terms of
          <placeName>America</placeName>’s engagement with the post-colonial Third World, right?And,
        again, the analogies between Americans fighting in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, in the
        context of French colonialism, certainly resonates in my—my personal feelings about
        Americans fighting in the Middle East in the—in the wake of British
        and French colonialism. You know, there’s the whole <name type="event">Sykes-Picot Treaty</name>
        [sic; Agreement] at he end of the <name type="event">First World War</name>
        that created the entire mess that we are in in the Middle East right
        now. And there is a kind of a tragic irony that American troops are once again dying because
        of what European powers did in the late 19th and early 20th centuries and even
        earlier, in what we call the Third World.It’s very—it raises a lot of interesting questions.
        I—I remain very ambivalent about the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience, about what
        it means, and it’s made me much less certain about—about politics, you know, generally. I—I
        think, you know, it also had a profound effect on me in terms of understanding who I am as a
        person [chuckles], right?—you know, how scared I can be.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">I’ve only been that scared once or twice in the rest of my life.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. Well, great. Yeah. So I—that’s—that was my—the last question I wanted to
        ask you. If you have any final thoughts or reflections that you would like to share, please
        feel free.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Sure. I—I guess I—I would—I would share these thoughts: that my—my four
          years at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, through happenstance, occurred at a period
        of tremendous change in American society, especially with Americans—American youth. I think
        that <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was a part, and a very important part, of that sea
        change in the way <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> students reacted to themselves and
        reacted to the world around them.I—I would observe that <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was an
        extremely protective place, but it was also a place that, during that period of time, more
        than I think it had in the past 30 or 40 years, opened itself out to change in
        the world in a different sort of way. I—some of my closest friends from
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> were in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> with me, and we all had—all took different
        roads.I think in terms of the overall American experience that, you know,
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> remains, for those of us who experienced it, certainly a
        seminal part of our lives. I think for your generation, oddly enough, it’s become much akin
        to the way <name type="event">the First World War</name> was for my generation. I remember
        as a young boy hearing my grandfather talk about the life in the trenches in the <name
          type="event">First World War</name>, and I suddenly realized, given the age
        differences, that my talking about being in a fishing village in
          <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> is not unlike that kind of a distant and retrospect vision
        into another—into another world.I’m encouraged by the fact that <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>
        is engaging with this. I think that—I’m encouraged by the fact that I think students at
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> are more aware of what it means to—to elect to be in the
        military, to serve in that kind of environment. And I hope that, you know, this project that
        you’re working on, you know, becomes part of the historical record and also remains
        available for, you know, <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> students in coming generations to see
        how their peers, who were part of a different <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you know, made
        the transition from <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, you know, to the wide, wide world and,
        you know, how we dealt, each of us individually, with a real set of fundamental changes in
        our—in our society.I remember thinking, during my years at
          <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, that the world was changing. The world was changing
        profoundly. And it was both because of the nature of what was happening in foreign policy
        but also because of what was happening culturally.And, again, I mentioned earlier in this
        conversation, music. I think that if you look at American contemporary music from <date when="1965">1965</date>
          to <date when="1969">1969</date>, the speed and the diversity and the power of change was really remarkable,
        and I think that part of made it so remarkable was the fact that it reflected these huge sea
        changes in society that surrounded <placeName>Hanover</placeName>. And one of the ways that
        really came to—you know, to affect us as students was through the music we were listening to
        and the issues that that music was dealing with.So I think that’s—that was going to be my
        summary. Thank you for giving me this opportunity. You know, I—I’m sure there are lots of
        very, very different—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Of course. Thank you very much.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">It was my pleasure. You know, and if you need anything for follow-up, you know
        where I am. I’m happy to help.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Of course. Thank you.</u>
      <u who="COOKE">Okay. Cheers.[End of interview.]</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
